<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-18T15:36:30-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Divine Joy</title><subtitle>The greatest satisfaction any human can experience is to enjoy God. I write to help others experience this divine joy.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Congregational Prayer for Unity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/prayers/2018/01/14/a-congregational-prayer-for-unity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Congregational Prayer for Unity" /><published>2018-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/prayers/2018/01/14/a-congregational-prayer-for-unity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/prayers/2018/01/14/a-congregational-prayer-for-unity.html">&lt;h4&gt;A Congregational Prayer for Unity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;I therefore, a prisoner for the Lord, urge you to walk in a manner worthy of the calling to which you have been called, with all humility and gentleness, with patience, bearing with one another in love, eager to maintain the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Ephesians 4:1-3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;GOD OVER ALL,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;You reign in heaven. In Your holiness, You created all things in unity with You and with others. In our wickedness, we hated Your authority. In Your greatness, for Your glory, You bore our curse to offer us Your righteousness. We rejoice in this news of Your goodness that You’ve made available to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;When You called us to Yourself, You breathed life into our hearts, and sealed us for redemption. We are adopted as a child of the Father, betrothed as the bride of Christ, built up as the temple of the Spirit, by Your grace, we have the hope of being brought into the perfect and eternal union with You, our Triune God. Let us, an embodiment of Your Church, display this unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;It is You who works in us both to will and work for Your good pleasure (Philippians 2:13). Let us remember our dependence on Your power and, in this humble condition, gently work to edify our body, teaching one another Your precious truths, reproving one another in false doctrines, correcting one another in righteousness, that we may be pure and blameless at Your return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Let us carry out this labor with all patience and perseverance. Let us remember that You alone give the growth, as we faithfully and trustingly labor for Your kingdom. In our brokenness, we’re quick to division, but, by Your power, let us be eager to maintain the unity we have in You. We ask these things in Your mighty name, for the display of Your glory through us, to the world, Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">A Congregational Prayer for Unity I therefore, a prisoner for the Lord, urge you to walk in a manner worthy of the calling to which you have been called, with all humility and gentleness, with patience, bearing with one another in love, eager to maintain the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. Ephesians 4:1-3 GOD OVER ALL, You reign in heaven. In Your holiness, You created all things in unity with You and with others. In our wickedness, we hated Your authority. In Your greatness, for Your glory, You bore our curse to offer us Your righteousness. We rejoice in this news of Your goodness that You’ve made available to us. When You called us to Yourself, You breathed life into our hearts, and sealed us for redemption. We are adopted as a child of the Father, betrothed as the bride of Christ, built up as the temple of the Spirit, by Your grace, we have the hope of being brought into the perfect and eternal union with You, our Triune God. Let us, an embodiment of Your Church, display this unity. It is You who works in us both to will and work for Your good pleasure (Philippians 2:13). Let us remember our dependence on Your power and, in this humble condition, gently work to edify our body, teaching one another Your precious truths, reproving one another in false doctrines, correcting one another in righteousness, that we may be pure and blameless at Your return. Let us carry out this labor with all patience and perseverance. Let us remember that You alone give the growth, as we faithfully and trustingly labor for Your kingdom. In our brokenness, we’re quick to division, but, by Your power, let us be eager to maintain the unity we have in You. We ask these things in Your mighty name, for the display of Your glory through us, to the world, Amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sufficient Grace in Exhausting Ministry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2018/01/10/sufficient-grace-in-exhausting-ministry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sufficient Grace in Exhausting Ministry" /><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/devotions/2018/01/10/sufficient-grace-in-exhausting-ministry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2018/01/10/sufficient-grace-in-exhausting-ministry.html">&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;But he said to me, &quot;My grace is sufficient for you, for my power is made perfect in weakness.&quot; Therefore I will boast all the more gladly of my weaknesses, so that the power of Christ may rest upon me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;2 Corinthians 12:9&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My responsibilities blinded me. I could not see what was going on in my life. I was striving to stay well, but, in my pride, I pressed on until I had nothing. I was spent. I was physically, emotionally, psychologically, and spiritually empty. I was anxious about my grades. I did not have time to complete projects and applications. I was trying to make life decisions. I was trying to be faithful in ministry. I was exhausted. My soul like a pot of boiling oil. It flowed. It turned. It tossed. It bubbled and spat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was at a ministry event, and the exhaustion and turmoil in my soul plagued me. During a moment of isolation, I felt as if I could not handle it. It continued for the next week. The next Thursday, I had just finished all my finals and intended to spend time with a good friend. I got coffee and ended up staying with him for around four hours. We had no agenda, and I laid out all that was weighing on me. I mentioned, not only this turmoil and exhaustion in me, but how I was preparing for a week of intense ministry. I felt entirely inadequate for this task and I was incredibly anxious over this. I debated not going. I feared I would hinder the work that would take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friday morning, I was still this way. As we walked through the airport, my team leader asked if anything was burdening my mind. I lied. I replied, &quot;Nope, I'm just tired.&quot; How grievous had I become? In my pride, I was deflecting spiritual aid from a loving brother. The Lord tore me down even me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praise be to Him; God mightily worked through me. He advanced His kingdom through me. Thanks be to God!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I was empty, exhausted, and unable to do this task, the steady hum that the gears of my spirit sang was &quot;My grace is sufficient for you, for my power is made perfect in weakness.&quot; The Lord sustained me through the weak. My soul was at rest. He lifted my spirit. I even had plenty of physical energy. My ability to serve was nothing short of a miracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just think, Friday morning, I am exhausted and defeated by the vanity and emptiness apart from Christ. But then, Saturday afternoon (and throughout the week), I am filled with wonder. My whole self is animated with joy, and I serve His kingdom with gladness. How else could this be, other than God's merciful power? Who else can receive glory for this than God?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God calls us into existence (Genesis 1:26-27), calls us to life in Christ by His Spirit (Ezekiel 37:9-10, John 10:27; 11). By His will and power, we also continue to exist (Colossians 1:17). Every resource we have—from our time and breath, to our spiritual vitality and desires—is from above. This is why we depend on grace. This is why it must be sufficient for us–because we have nothing else to suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is Paul's response to recognizing His weakness? It is gladness! Paul is filled with joy. Why? Because God, in His infinite wisdom, has seen it fit to glorify Himself by using our dead souls to resurrect, redeem, and restore His creation. God does this—He wins our hearts for the worship that He already deserves—for His good pleasure, and we are glad beneficiaries of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this old hymn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Should nothing of our efforts stand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;No legacy survive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Unless the Lord does raise the house&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;In vain its builders strive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;All Glory Be to Christ – Robert Burns (1759-1796)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;GRACIOUS FATHER, may our hearts resound with this truth. Let it reverberate through all our essence. Motivate us to kill our pride. Calm us to rest in Christ's righteousness and Your Spirit's power in all our labors. Fill us with the joy of Your Sprit, and let us join in glad service to all, for Your glory among all. In Christ's name, Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">But he said to me, &quot;My grace is sufficient for you, for my power is made perfect in weakness.&quot; Therefore I will boast all the more gladly of my weaknesses, so that the power of Christ may rest upon me. 2 Corinthians 12:9 Here is a story: My responsibilities blinded me. I could not see what was going on in my life. I was striving to stay well, but, in my pride, I pressed on until I had nothing. I was spent. I was physically, emotionally, psychologically, and spiritually empty. I was anxious about my grades. I did not have time to complete projects and applications. I was trying to make life decisions. I was trying to be faithful in ministry. I was exhausted. My soul like a pot of boiling oil. It flowed. It turned. It tossed. It bubbled and spat. I was at a ministry event, and the exhaustion and turmoil in my soul plagued me. During a moment of isolation, I felt as if I could not handle it. It continued for the next week. The next Thursday, I had just finished all my finals and intended to spend time with a good friend. I got coffee and ended up staying with him for around four hours. We had no agenda, and I laid out all that was weighing on me. I mentioned, not only this turmoil and exhaustion in me, but how I was preparing for a week of intense ministry. I felt entirely inadequate for this task and I was incredibly anxious over this. I debated not going. I feared I would hinder the work that would take place. Friday morning, I was still this way. As we walked through the airport, my team leader asked if anything was burdening my mind. I lied. I replied, &quot;Nope, I'm just tired.&quot; How grievous had I become? In my pride, I was deflecting spiritual aid from a loving brother. The Lord tore me down even me. Praise be to Him; God mightily worked through me. He advanced His kingdom through me. Thanks be to God! Though I was empty, exhausted, and unable to do this task, the steady hum that the gears of my spirit sang was &quot;My grace is sufficient for you, for my power is made perfect in weakness.&quot; The Lord sustained me through the weak. My soul was at rest. He lifted my spirit. I even had plenty of physical energy. My ability to serve was nothing short of a miracle. Just think, Friday morning, I am exhausted and defeated by the vanity and emptiness apart from Christ. But then, Saturday afternoon (and throughout the week), I am filled with wonder. My whole self is animated with joy, and I serve His kingdom with gladness. How else could this be, other than God's merciful power? Who else can receive glory for this than God? God calls us into existence (Genesis 1:26-27), calls us to life in Christ by His Spirit (Ezekiel 37:9-10, John 10:27; 11). By His will and power, we also continue to exist (Colossians 1:17). Every resource we have—from our time and breath, to our spiritual vitality and desires—is from above. This is why we depend on grace. This is why it must be sufficient for us–because we have nothing else to suffice. So, what is Paul's response to recognizing His weakness? It is gladness! Paul is filled with joy. Why? Because God, in His infinite wisdom, has seen it fit to glorify Himself by using our dead souls to resurrect, redeem, and restore His creation. God does this—He wins our hearts for the worship that He already deserves—for His good pleasure, and we are glad beneficiaries of this. Consider this old hymn: Should nothing of our efforts stand No legacy survive Unless the Lord does raise the house In vain its builders strive All Glory Be to Christ – Robert Burns (1759-1796) GRACIOUS FATHER, may our hearts resound with this truth. Let it reverberate through all our essence. Motivate us to kill our pride. Calm us to rest in Christ's righteousness and Your Spirit's power in all our labors. Fill us with the joy of Your Sprit, and let us join in glad service to all, for Your glory among all. In Christ's name, Amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unity Amidst Diversity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/messages/2018/01/07/unity-amidst-diversity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unity Amidst Diversity" /><published>2018-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/messages/2018/01/07/unity-amidst-diversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/messages/2018/01/07/unity-amidst-diversity.html">&lt;p&gt;Opening Prayer
LORD,
Unless You build Your house, we labor in vain.
Please work through me now, to build up Your house.
In Christ name I pray, Amen.
Sermon
Introduction
I remember that one of the first times I could drive after I got my license, I was going to a friend’s birthday party. It was fun, and I was headed home around 8 o’clock or so because I had a curfew. But, being that late on a November night, it was pretty dark outside. In fact, if I remember correctly, it might have started to rain.
Another friend of mine that was leaving about the same time still only had his permit, so his dad was going to make him take some backroads home just so he’d get the experience. I’ve always been a fan of taking backroads when I’m the one driving, so, naturally, I followed them.
After a while, I realized how long it was going to take, so I decide that I’d just cut back over to the main road. This was my first mistake. What I did wrong, was assume I knew which way the main road was. I made a turn, followed it to a dead end, and realized I was in trouble.
Now you may think, “Oh, that’s no big deal. You can just look up the directions on your phone.” The problem with that was that my phone was dead and I didn’t have a charger. So, there I was, a sixteen year old kid, in the middle of somewhere I’d never been, pitch black outside, raining, with no idea where I was. At that point, I realized just how important it is to know where you’ve been, and how you got to where you are.
I think a similar thing can be said of history. It’s important to know where we were before and how we got to the point we’re at now, so that we can know how to get to where we’re headed.
Today, with the topic of “God and Race” in mind, we find ourselves in a passage where Paul is explaining to the members of the Ephesian church where they were, where they’re at, and where they’re headed.
So, with that in outline in mind, I invite you to look with me at Ephesians chapter 2 verse 11.
If you don’t have a Bible with you, you can find it on page _____ in the pew Bible.
If you’re not used to looking at a Bible, I’m glad you’re here, the big numbers are the chapters and the little numbers are the verses. So, to find the section we’re looking at, you’ll look for the book of Ephesians, then look for the big number 2 and then the little number 11.
If you will, let’s stand in honor of the reading of God’s Word. Ephesians chapter 2 verse 11,
So then, remember that at one time you were Gentiles in the flesh–called “the uncircumcised” by those called “the circumcised,” which is done in the flesh by human hands. At that time you were without the Messiah, excluded from the citizenship of Israel, and foreigners to the covenants of promise, without hope and without God in this world. But now in Christ Jesus, you who were far away have been brought near by the blood of the Messiah. For He is our peace, who made both groups one and tore down the dividing wall of hostility. In His flesh He made of no effect the law consisting of commands and expressed in regulations, so that He might create in Himself one new man from the two, resulting in peace. He did this so that He might reconcile both to God in one body through the cross and put hostility to death by it. When the Messiah came, He proclaimed the good news of peace to those who were far away and peace to those who were near. For through Him we both have access by one Spirit to the Father. So then, you are no longer foreigners and strangers, but fellow citizens with the saints and members of God’s household, built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets with Christ Jesus Himself as the cornerstone. The whole building being put together by Him, grows into a holy sanctuary in the Lord. You are also being built together for God’s dwelling in the Spirit. [Ephesians 2:11-22]
This is the Word of God; thanks be to Him. You may be seated.
In this passage of Scripture, Paul is telling us our history as the people of God.
His main point in writing this letter to the Ephesian church, is unity. This is the key, if you will, that Paul is playing in throughout the entire letter.
In fact, Paul greets the church in chapter 1 verse 2 with the standard greeting of both Greeks and Jews when he says, “Grace and peace.” Then, in his farewell in chapter 6, Paul reverses the order when he says, “peace and grace.” From beginning to end, Unity is the central idea. But how do we have unity? Who exactly has this unity? And how does this have anything to do with race?
The point Paul is making is that true unity is only found in the people of God, who have been unified by God’s saving work. This includes every social class, every language, every political party, and every race.
So, with unity in mind, this passage we’re looking at has three main parts of our history. First, in verses 11 through 12, Paul tells us of the division that existed between the Jews and the Gentiles. Then, in verses 13 through 18, Paul tells us of Christ’s unifying work. Finally, in verses 19 through 22, Paul tells us of the unity that we now have in Christ.
Our Divided Past (v.11-12)
So, Paul’s first section of our history is our divided past. Specifically, he’s discussing the division between Jews and Gentiles. Look with me at verse 11 again,
So then, remember that at one time you were Gentiles in the flesh–called “the uncircumcised” by those called “the circumcised,” [Ephesians 2:11a]
Here, Paul is reminding the Gentile Christians of their past, and of the division that was between them and the Jews. Paul reminds them of the label that they were frequently known by, “the uncircumcised.” Who called them this? The circumcised Jews of the day.
Right away, Paul’s drawing the picture of division between the Jews and the Gentiles with the distinguishing mark of God’s people in the Old Testament: circumcision.
You see, the Jews didn’t just practice circumcision for health purposes, this was a sign that was given to them by God to separate themselves from the other nations surrounding them. You can see back in Genesis that as God called Abraham and promised to make a people for Himself, God also commanded that Abraham be circumcised. Circumcision was an outward sign of entrance into the covenant community of God’s people.
The Jews were in this covenant community. Gentiles were outside of this community. And, as verse 11 suggests, the Jews made sure that the Gentiles knew they were excluded because of the circumcision.
Throughout Israel’s history, they still practiced this command of God. It was administered on the 8th day after the birth of a baby boy, so that every male Jew was circumcised.
However, despite Israel keeping this command, they lost the purpose–the meaning behind the practice. The Jews became prideful in this sign. They placed their faith in their circumcision, not the God who commanded it.
In fact, they became so obsessed with this sign that it became the single factor in whether they’d consider one a Jew or not. This one act, determined whether a person would be considered favored by God or not. In another letter, Paul refers to these Jews obsessed with circumcision as “dogs,…evil workers,…those who mutilate the flesh…” (Philippians 3:3)
What are the implications of this division, though? What’s the big deal about not being in the group of the Jews? Paul answers this in verse 12,
At that time, you were without the Messiah, excluded from the citizenship of Israel, and foreigners to the covenants of promise, without hope and without God in the world. [Ephesians 2:12]
The division between the Jews and Gentiles goes far deeper that simply belonging to a group or not. The Jews had a promise from God that they would be redeemed. God, from the very beginning, promised His people that He would send a Messiah.
Now, since the Gentiles were excluded from citizenship to Israel, they were considered foreigners to the promises of God. Namely, that they were foreigners to the promise of God’s redemption through a Savior.
But what redemption did God promise? Right before this passage, in verses 1 through 3 of chapter 2, Paul tells us that we are dead in our trespasses and sins and facing God’s wrath.
Friends, we’ve all affronted God’s authority. In our hearts and in our actions, we’ve rebelled against God’s good and perfect commands. And now, we stand before Him, the good and just judge, and rightly deserve punishment. How can a good God allow evil to just be swept away under an eternal rug? If God is to be good, He must condemn evil, and that means condemning our sin.
The goodness of the gospel, however, is that God is both good, and merciful. In God’s goodness, He doesn’t just sweep evil under the rug, He deals with it. But God, in His mercy, Has come in person, taken the sins of His people on Himself, and offered Himself as a sacrifice for them.
But these Gentiles didn’t have the promise of a redeeming Messiah, and therefore, they had no hope to which they could look forward. And without this hope, they were without God. They could not know Him. Not that God was entirely disinterested with them, but that they couldn’t call God their Father. The only way they could know God was as the Holy King of the Universe against which they rebelled. The only way they could know God was the Good and Perfect Judge who would one day condemn all evil, which included them.
Friends, this is our history. We’ve all rebelled against God. Not one of us has kept His commandments. This is why we need the hope of the gospel.
If you’re a non-Christian here today. I’m going to risk offending you by telling you that this is also you, right now. Even if you’ve been to church your entire life. Unless we turn from our sin, from our rebellion against God, and trust in His saving work on the cross, you face this wrath. You are without hope and without God.
Christ’s Unifying Work (v.13-18)
The next section of our history that Paul’s describes in verses 13 through 18 is Christ’s unifying work.
We already saw the division Paul pictured in verses 11 and 12, but Paul addresses the resolution to this problem. Verse 13 says,
But now, in Christ Jesus, you who were far away have been brought near by the blood of the Messiah. [Ephesians 2:13]
How is this division resolved? Through Christ’s blood of the cross. This large chasm between the Jews and the Gentiles, between God’s people, and those not has now been closed by Christ’s blood.
But what’s so special about Christ’s blood? Why is this important for making unity? Earlier in this letter Paul wrote,
We have redemption in Him, through His blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses. [Ephesians 1:7]
Friend, through Christ’s blood alone, do we have forgiveness of our trespasses. Christ’s sacrifice on the cross was not limited to only Jews. God didn’t only redeem people from Israel, but from every nation.
Not only are the far away Gentiles brought near, but we see that Christ has made the two groups one. The Gentiles, who were excluded from the members of God’s people, far away from God’s people, were brought into the circle of God’s people.
We are now unified in Christ, who is our peace. How did Christ do this though? How did He unify both Jews and Gentiles? Paul gives us two answers: the first is that Christ tore down the dividing wall of hostility. In verse 14, he says,
For He is our peace, who made both groups one and tore down the dividing wall of hostility… [Ephesians 2:14]
What Paul means is that Christ died for both Jews and Gentiles on the Cross. He grouped them both together in His sacrifice. Christ’s death on the cross outed all of us as equal before God. That may sound like good news, but, at least to some degree, that’s tragic news. Just think, we are all so sinful that we needed the incarnate God to die in our place. One Puritan meditated on it this way,
Thy blood is the blood of incarnate God,
  its worth infinite, its value beyond all thought.
Infinite must be the evil and guilt
that demands such a price.
[The Precious Blood – Valley of Vision]
If our sin was so wicked and evil that it demanded the blood of God’s only Son, we can see that we all are equal before God, but that our equality is our deserving hell. Indeed, Christ tore down this dividing wall by revealing our common need for salvation.
Look with me at the end of verse 14 though. Paul continues,
In His flesh, He made of no effect the law consisting of commands and expressed in regulations, so that He might create one new man from the two, resulting in peace. [Ephesians 2:14b-15a]
The second answer Paul gives us as to how Christ made both groups one is that Christ made the law of no effect. It’s paid. It’s fulfilled. We no longer have the guilt of our disobedience hanging over our heads because Christ came and lived in perfect obedience to the law, and now offers us that perfection through faith.
Again, in verse 16, Paul makes it doubly clear what Christ’s intentions were,
He did this so that He might reconcile both the God in one body through the cross and put hostility to death by it. [Ephesians 2:16]
We all owed a common debt, and Christ paid our common debt. We all stood equally guilty before God, but now, for those in Him, we stand equally in our faith in Christ’s salvation. He’s put hostility between the earthly races to death by unifying us in Christ’s death and resurrection.
Friend, that’s great news! We deserved death, but Christ took our death in our place. This great divide and hostility between the Jews and Gentiles was put to death. Our common need for a Savior was exposed by God coming in the flesh to pay for our sins, and He’s provided a common bond for His people in their salvation through faith in Him.
If you’re a non-Christian here today, I wonder how you think about this? You might ask, “can these two groups really be brought together?”, “Could this really happen today?” The answer scripture gives us is an emphatic YES!
You see, when God exposed our need for a Savior, He showed the deepest core of each person. Namely, that we were rebels against our very Creator. He showed the evil thoughts and intention in each of our hearts. These may not come across as what we imagine as evil. We might think, “Oh, a little lie isn’t evil,” but, friends, by lying we’re telling God that we think we know better than Him, and that means holding up what is false instead of what is true, so that we can gain. You see, our deepest selves, have the tendency to disregard God’s authority. That’s our evil.
Now, since our deepest need is a Savior, they our greatest joy must be if that Savior is provided. This is how we are unified. God’s people are unified by their common, deepest joy in Christ.
Now, non-Christian, I don’t mean to exclude you–in fact, I invite to join, to repent and believe in Christ–but this unity is only offered through faith in Christ. So I urge you this morning to consider your rebellion from God, consider your inability to be keep God’s perfect and good law, and trust in Christ who offers us His perfect life.
Moving on, this news isn’t just available to all, it is to be proclaimed to all, look at verse 17. Paul writes,
When the Messiah came, He proclaimed the good news of peace to you who were far away, and peace to those who were near. [Ephesians 2:17]
This peace that Christ made through the cross, He proclaimed to all people. Jew and Gentile, rich and poor. Every social class, every language, every political position, and every race. Christ has unified all of His people, and as His followers, we’re follow Him in this.
This is why we’re commanded to take the gospel to areas of the world where they’ve never heard it. Christ has offered them salvation but they’ve never heard. This is why we pray fervently for God to send people to them, and labor at home to teach the gospel in our communities.
Keep going to verse 18,
For through Him we both have access by one Spirit to the Father. [Ephesians 2:18]
We have salvation through a single Christ, by a single Spirit and a single Father. There’s not a salvation for Jews here, and a salvation for Gentiles here. We both, as a new people of God, have access to God by a single sacrifice, which is God Himself.
Unity Created (v.19-22)
So Paul has shown us our divided past, and Paul has shown us Christ’s unifying work. Now, the final section of our history that Paul mentions is the unity that Christ has created. Paul uses three images to describe our unity that we have in Christ.
The first image Paul uses to describe our unity in Christ is fellow citizens of a divine kingdom. In verse 19 Paul says,
So then, you are no longer foreigners and strangers, but fellow citizens with the saints… [Ephesians 2:19]
This reminiscent of the issue Paul brought up earlier in our text. In verse 12 Paul said,
…you were without the messiah, excluded from the citizenship of Israel, and foreigners to the covenants of promise… [Ephesians 2:12]
Paul’s reminding the Gentiles that they are no longer aliens to God’s kingdom, but that they have been brought into God’s divine kingdom, granted full citizenship, and lavished with all the benefits of their heavenly home.
Another way Paul gives us to think about our unity in Christ is as members of God’s family. The last part of verse 19 says,
…And members of God’s household… [Ephesians 2:19b]
Earlier in this letter, Paul wrote,
He predestined us to be adopted through Jesus Christ for Himself, according to His favor and will… [Ephesians 1:5]
In Paul’s letter to the Romans, he wrote,
For you did not receive a spirit of slavery to fall back into fear, but you received the Spirit of adoption, by whom we cry out, “Abba, Father!” [Romans 8:15]
For those who have trusted in Christ, God has saved us, and adopted us into His family. He is no longer the judge sure to deliver His wrath to us, but that wrath has been delivered to Christ and now we who made ourselves enemies of God are now adopted as His children.
The final image Paul gives us to understand our unity in Christ is as building blocks of God’s temple. Verses 20 through 22 say,
Built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, with Christ Jesus Himself as the cornerstone. The whole building, being put together by Him, grows into a holy sanctuary in the Lord. You are also being built together for God’s dwelling in the Spirit. [Ephesians 2:20-22]
The picture that Paul’s painting here is similar to how we’d build a Lincoln Log cabin. First, you need a solid foundation to build on. That’s Christ. Then we have the little flat pieces that start off the building with. That’s the apostles and prophets. Then there’s the rest of the pieces that get added on top.
In the same way, God is building a people for Himself. They’re all knitted and locked together. Firmly situated on Christ.
So, just as fellow citizens in a nation, and just as members of a family, and just as building blocks of a building, for those of us in Christ–that is, for those who turn from our sin and trust in God for salvation–we now stand unified.
Implications of this Unity (4:1-3)
So what does this mean for us? For us who, by faith, are members of God’s people now, what does it mean for us to be unified? There are numerous implications, but let me submit just one to you this morning. Look with me to chapter 4 verse 1.
Therefore I, the prisoner for the Lord, urge you to walk worthy of the calling you have received, with all humility and gentleness, with patience accepting one another in love, diligently keeping the unity of the Spirit with the peace that binds us. [Ephesians 4:1-3]
For us who are unified in Christ, we are commanded to strive for deeper unity.
We are called to labor for this peace. Specifically regarding racial tension, this means recognizing inequality around us. It means recognizing privileges that one group might have over another.
Brothers and sisters, we cannot simply be color-blind. Now, here me. I am by no means saying that we should hold stigmas or stereotypes against people. What I’m saying is that, in order for us to follow this command to keep unity and accept one another in love, we have to recognize the lives of our brothers and sisters who are of a different race.
For example, I have an African-American friend–one of the friendliest guys you’ll ever meet. He served in the Marines, so he’s this really big, tough-looking guy, but he’s also in band and he wants to be a weather man, so he’s kind of like a teddy bear.
But he was telling me how, at one point in his teenage years, that his father sat him down, and very seriously told him that he’s going to be treated differently. That simply because of his skin color, he’s going to have to live with the baggage of the stereotype that existed. He was going to have a difficult time with police, he’s going to intimidate people, and so on.
Brothers and sisters, if we’re going to strive for deeper unity–if we’re truly going to accept one another in love, we must understand the lives that our brothers and sisters live. We have to understand the privilege we might have of not worrying how the police might treat us or not worrying that we might intimidate some lady that we’re passing on the street.
We can’t just understand these things, but we have to be advocates to put these things away. We have to advocate for not just equality in treatment, but equality in privilege.
Friends, this won’t be easy. It takes a lot of effort.
Therefore I, the prisoner for the Lord, urge you to walk worthy of the calling you have received, with all humility and gentleness, with patience accepting one another in love, diligently keeping the unity of the Spirit with the peace that binds us. [Ephesians 4:1-3]
Paul front-loads this command with a lot of phrases. He mentions, humility, gentleness, patience, and diligence.
Brothers and sisters, this labor will be long and hard, but as unified members of God’s household, this labor is worth it.
Christ did not leave us divide. He sought His people, died for them on the cross, and reconciling both to God in one body. A body that now exists in part, on earth today. If we are to follow our Lord, we must cherish our unified hope, and seek deeper unity.
But let me remind you, we will not have perfect unity on this earth. Our hope is heaven where, as Revelation 7 tells, us,
After this I looked, and there was a vast multitude from every nation, tribe, people, and language, which no one could number, standing before the throne and before the Lamb. They were robed in white with palm branches in their hands. And they cried out in a loud voice:
Salvation belongs to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb!
[Revelation 7:9-10]
Let’s pray.
Closing Prayer
GREAT GOD,
You created the heavens and the earth. We come before You, thanking You for Your Word. May we now respond with our lives.
We long for the day when we will be gathered with the diverse multitude and declare: Salvation belongs to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.
Until then, may we seek unity amidst racial diversity in our communities, but especially in the Church, Your body, Your bride.
We know we cannot do this on our own, so we humble petition You. May it be so.
We ask in Christ’s name, Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">Opening Prayer LORD, Unless You build Your house, we labor in vain. Please work through me now, to build up Your house. In Christ name I pray, Amen. Sermon Introduction I remember that one of the first times I could drive after I got my license, I was going to a friend’s birthday party. It was fun, and I was headed home around 8 o’clock or so because I had a curfew. But, being that late on a November night, it was pretty dark outside. In fact, if I remember correctly, it might have started to rain. Another friend of mine that was leaving about the same time still only had his permit, so his dad was going to make him take some backroads home just so he’d get the experience. I’ve always been a fan of taking backroads when I’m the one driving, so, naturally, I followed them. After a while, I realized how long it was going to take, so I decide that I’d just cut back over to the main road. This was my first mistake. What I did wrong, was assume I knew which way the main road was. I made a turn, followed it to a dead end, and realized I was in trouble. Now you may think, “Oh, that’s no big deal. You can just look up the directions on your phone.” The problem with that was that my phone was dead and I didn’t have a charger. So, there I was, a sixteen year old kid, in the middle of somewhere I’d never been, pitch black outside, raining, with no idea where I was. At that point, I realized just how important it is to know where you’ve been, and how you got to where you are. I think a similar thing can be said of history. It’s important to know where we were before and how we got to the point we’re at now, so that we can know how to get to where we’re headed. Today, with the topic of “God and Race” in mind, we find ourselves in a passage where Paul is explaining to the members of the Ephesian church where they were, where they’re at, and where they’re headed. So, with that in outline in mind, I invite you to look with me at Ephesians chapter 2 verse 11. If you don’t have a Bible with you, you can find it on page _____ in the pew Bible. If you’re not used to looking at a Bible, I’m glad you’re here, the big numbers are the chapters and the little numbers are the verses. So, to find the section we’re looking at, you’ll look for the book of Ephesians, then look for the big number 2 and then the little number 11. If you will, let’s stand in honor of the reading of God’s Word. Ephesians chapter 2 verse 11, So then, remember that at one time you were Gentiles in the flesh–called “the uncircumcised” by those called “the circumcised,” which is done in the flesh by human hands. At that time you were without the Messiah, excluded from the citizenship of Israel, and foreigners to the covenants of promise, without hope and without God in this world. But now in Christ Jesus, you who were far away have been brought near by the blood of the Messiah. For He is our peace, who made both groups one and tore down the dividing wall of hostility. In His flesh He made of no effect the law consisting of commands and expressed in regulations, so that He might create in Himself one new man from the two, resulting in peace. He did this so that He might reconcile both to God in one body through the cross and put hostility to death by it. When the Messiah came, He proclaimed the good news of peace to those who were far away and peace to those who were near. For through Him we both have access by one Spirit to the Father. So then, you are no longer foreigners and strangers, but fellow citizens with the saints and members of God’s household, built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets with Christ Jesus Himself as the cornerstone. The whole building being put together by Him, grows into a holy sanctuary in the Lord. You are also being built together for God’s dwelling in the Spirit. [Ephesians 2:11-22] This is the Word of God; thanks be to Him. You may be seated. In this passage of Scripture, Paul is telling us our history as the people of God. His main point in writing this letter to the Ephesian church, is unity. This is the key, if you will, that Paul is playing in throughout the entire letter. In fact, Paul greets the church in chapter 1 verse 2 with the standard greeting of both Greeks and Jews when he says, “Grace and peace.” Then, in his farewell in chapter 6, Paul reverses the order when he says, “peace and grace.” From beginning to end, Unity is the central idea. But how do we have unity? Who exactly has this unity? And how does this have anything to do with race? The point Paul is making is that true unity is only found in the people of God, who have been unified by God’s saving work. This includes every social class, every language, every political party, and every race. So, with unity in mind, this passage we’re looking at has three main parts of our history. First, in verses 11 through 12, Paul tells us of the division that existed between the Jews and the Gentiles. Then, in verses 13 through 18, Paul tells us of Christ’s unifying work. Finally, in verses 19 through 22, Paul tells us of the unity that we now have in Christ. Our Divided Past (v.11-12) So, Paul’s first section of our history is our divided past. Specifically, he’s discussing the division between Jews and Gentiles. Look with me at verse 11 again, So then, remember that at one time you were Gentiles in the flesh–called “the uncircumcised” by those called “the circumcised,” [Ephesians 2:11a] Here, Paul is reminding the Gentile Christians of their past, and of the division that was between them and the Jews. Paul reminds them of the label that they were frequently known by, “the uncircumcised.” Who called them this? The circumcised Jews of the day. Right away, Paul’s drawing the picture of division between the Jews and the Gentiles with the distinguishing mark of God’s people in the Old Testament: circumcision. You see, the Jews didn’t just practice circumcision for health purposes, this was a sign that was given to them by God to separate themselves from the other nations surrounding them. You can see back in Genesis that as God called Abraham and promised to make a people for Himself, God also commanded that Abraham be circumcised. Circumcision was an outward sign of entrance into the covenant community of God’s people. The Jews were in this covenant community. Gentiles were outside of this community. And, as verse 11 suggests, the Jews made sure that the Gentiles knew they were excluded because of the circumcision. Throughout Israel’s history, they still practiced this command of God. It was administered on the 8th day after the birth of a baby boy, so that every male Jew was circumcised. However, despite Israel keeping this command, they lost the purpose–the meaning behind the practice. The Jews became prideful in this sign. They placed their faith in their circumcision, not the God who commanded it. In fact, they became so obsessed with this sign that it became the single factor in whether they’d consider one a Jew or not. This one act, determined whether a person would be considered favored by God or not. In another letter, Paul refers to these Jews obsessed with circumcision as “dogs,…evil workers,…those who mutilate the flesh…” (Philippians 3:3) What are the implications of this division, though? What’s the big deal about not being in the group of the Jews? Paul answers this in verse 12, At that time, you were without the Messiah, excluded from the citizenship of Israel, and foreigners to the covenants of promise, without hope and without God in the world. [Ephesians 2:12] The division between the Jews and Gentiles goes far deeper that simply belonging to a group or not. The Jews had a promise from God that they would be redeemed. God, from the very beginning, promised His people that He would send a Messiah. Now, since the Gentiles were excluded from citizenship to Israel, they were considered foreigners to the promises of God. Namely, that they were foreigners to the promise of God’s redemption through a Savior. But what redemption did God promise? Right before this passage, in verses 1 through 3 of chapter 2, Paul tells us that we are dead in our trespasses and sins and facing God’s wrath. Friends, we’ve all affronted God’s authority. In our hearts and in our actions, we’ve rebelled against God’s good and perfect commands. And now, we stand before Him, the good and just judge, and rightly deserve punishment. How can a good God allow evil to just be swept away under an eternal rug? If God is to be good, He must condemn evil, and that means condemning our sin. The goodness of the gospel, however, is that God is both good, and merciful. In God’s goodness, He doesn’t just sweep evil under the rug, He deals with it. But God, in His mercy, Has come in person, taken the sins of His people on Himself, and offered Himself as a sacrifice for them. But these Gentiles didn’t have the promise of a redeeming Messiah, and therefore, they had no hope to which they could look forward. And without this hope, they were without God. They could not know Him. Not that God was entirely disinterested with them, but that they couldn’t call God their Father. The only way they could know God was as the Holy King of the Universe against which they rebelled. The only way they could know God was the Good and Perfect Judge who would one day condemn all evil, which included them. Friends, this is our history. We’ve all rebelled against God. Not one of us has kept His commandments. This is why we need the hope of the gospel. If you’re a non-Christian here today. I’m going to risk offending you by telling you that this is also you, right now. Even if you’ve been to church your entire life. Unless we turn from our sin, from our rebellion against God, and trust in His saving work on the cross, you face this wrath. You are without hope and without God. Christ’s Unifying Work (v.13-18) The next section of our history that Paul’s describes in verses 13 through 18 is Christ’s unifying work. We already saw the division Paul pictured in verses 11 and 12, but Paul addresses the resolution to this problem. Verse 13 says, But now, in Christ Jesus, you who were far away have been brought near by the blood of the Messiah. [Ephesians 2:13] How is this division resolved? Through Christ’s blood of the cross. This large chasm between the Jews and the Gentiles, between God’s people, and those not has now been closed by Christ’s blood. But what’s so special about Christ’s blood? Why is this important for making unity? Earlier in this letter Paul wrote, We have redemption in Him, through His blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses. [Ephesians 1:7] Friend, through Christ’s blood alone, do we have forgiveness of our trespasses. Christ’s sacrifice on the cross was not limited to only Jews. God didn’t only redeem people from Israel, but from every nation. Not only are the far away Gentiles brought near, but we see that Christ has made the two groups one. The Gentiles, who were excluded from the members of God’s people, far away from God’s people, were brought into the circle of God’s people. We are now unified in Christ, who is our peace. How did Christ do this though? How did He unify both Jews and Gentiles? Paul gives us two answers: the first is that Christ tore down the dividing wall of hostility. In verse 14, he says, For He is our peace, who made both groups one and tore down the dividing wall of hostility… [Ephesians 2:14] What Paul means is that Christ died for both Jews and Gentiles on the Cross. He grouped them both together in His sacrifice. Christ’s death on the cross outed all of us as equal before God. That may sound like good news, but, at least to some degree, that’s tragic news. Just think, we are all so sinful that we needed the incarnate God to die in our place. One Puritan meditated on it this way, Thy blood is the blood of incarnate God, its worth infinite, its value beyond all thought. Infinite must be the evil and guilt that demands such a price. [The Precious Blood – Valley of Vision] If our sin was so wicked and evil that it demanded the blood of God’s only Son, we can see that we all are equal before God, but that our equality is our deserving hell. Indeed, Christ tore down this dividing wall by revealing our common need for salvation. Look with me at the end of verse 14 though. Paul continues, In His flesh, He made of no effect the law consisting of commands and expressed in regulations, so that He might create one new man from the two, resulting in peace. [Ephesians 2:14b-15a] The second answer Paul gives us as to how Christ made both groups one is that Christ made the law of no effect. It’s paid. It’s fulfilled. We no longer have the guilt of our disobedience hanging over our heads because Christ came and lived in perfect obedience to the law, and now offers us that perfection through faith. Again, in verse 16, Paul makes it doubly clear what Christ’s intentions were, He did this so that He might reconcile both the God in one body through the cross and put hostility to death by it. [Ephesians 2:16] We all owed a common debt, and Christ paid our common debt. We all stood equally guilty before God, but now, for those in Him, we stand equally in our faith in Christ’s salvation. He’s put hostility between the earthly races to death by unifying us in Christ’s death and resurrection. Friend, that’s great news! We deserved death, but Christ took our death in our place. This great divide and hostility between the Jews and Gentiles was put to death. Our common need for a Savior was exposed by God coming in the flesh to pay for our sins, and He’s provided a common bond for His people in their salvation through faith in Him. If you’re a non-Christian here today, I wonder how you think about this? You might ask, “can these two groups really be brought together?”, “Could this really happen today?” The answer scripture gives us is an emphatic YES! You see, when God exposed our need for a Savior, He showed the deepest core of each person. Namely, that we were rebels against our very Creator. He showed the evil thoughts and intention in each of our hearts. These may not come across as what we imagine as evil. We might think, “Oh, a little lie isn’t evil,” but, friends, by lying we’re telling God that we think we know better than Him, and that means holding up what is false instead of what is true, so that we can gain. You see, our deepest selves, have the tendency to disregard God’s authority. That’s our evil. Now, since our deepest need is a Savior, they our greatest joy must be if that Savior is provided. This is how we are unified. God’s people are unified by their common, deepest joy in Christ. Now, non-Christian, I don’t mean to exclude you–in fact, I invite to join, to repent and believe in Christ–but this unity is only offered through faith in Christ. So I urge you this morning to consider your rebellion from God, consider your inability to be keep God’s perfect and good law, and trust in Christ who offers us His perfect life. Moving on, this news isn’t just available to all, it is to be proclaimed to all, look at verse 17. Paul writes, When the Messiah came, He proclaimed the good news of peace to you who were far away, and peace to those who were near. [Ephesians 2:17] This peace that Christ made through the cross, He proclaimed to all people. Jew and Gentile, rich and poor. Every social class, every language, every political position, and every race. Christ has unified all of His people, and as His followers, we’re follow Him in this. This is why we’re commanded to take the gospel to areas of the world where they’ve never heard it. Christ has offered them salvation but they’ve never heard. This is why we pray fervently for God to send people to them, and labor at home to teach the gospel in our communities. Keep going to verse 18, For through Him we both have access by one Spirit to the Father. [Ephesians 2:18] We have salvation through a single Christ, by a single Spirit and a single Father. There’s not a salvation for Jews here, and a salvation for Gentiles here. We both, as a new people of God, have access to God by a single sacrifice, which is God Himself. Unity Created (v.19-22) So Paul has shown us our divided past, and Paul has shown us Christ’s unifying work. Now, the final section of our history that Paul mentions is the unity that Christ has created. Paul uses three images to describe our unity that we have in Christ. The first image Paul uses to describe our unity in Christ is fellow citizens of a divine kingdom. In verse 19 Paul says, So then, you are no longer foreigners and strangers, but fellow citizens with the saints… [Ephesians 2:19] This reminiscent of the issue Paul brought up earlier in our text. In verse 12 Paul said, …you were without the messiah, excluded from the citizenship of Israel, and foreigners to the covenants of promise… [Ephesians 2:12] Paul’s reminding the Gentiles that they are no longer aliens to God’s kingdom, but that they have been brought into God’s divine kingdom, granted full citizenship, and lavished with all the benefits of their heavenly home. Another way Paul gives us to think about our unity in Christ is as members of God’s family. The last part of verse 19 says, …And members of God’s household… [Ephesians 2:19b] Earlier in this letter, Paul wrote, He predestined us to be adopted through Jesus Christ for Himself, according to His favor and will… [Ephesians 1:5] In Paul’s letter to the Romans, he wrote, For you did not receive a spirit of slavery to fall back into fear, but you received the Spirit of adoption, by whom we cry out, “Abba, Father!” [Romans 8:15] For those who have trusted in Christ, God has saved us, and adopted us into His family. He is no longer the judge sure to deliver His wrath to us, but that wrath has been delivered to Christ and now we who made ourselves enemies of God are now adopted as His children. The final image Paul gives us to understand our unity in Christ is as building blocks of God’s temple. Verses 20 through 22 say, Built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, with Christ Jesus Himself as the cornerstone. The whole building, being put together by Him, grows into a holy sanctuary in the Lord. You are also being built together for God’s dwelling in the Spirit. [Ephesians 2:20-22] The picture that Paul’s painting here is similar to how we’d build a Lincoln Log cabin. First, you need a solid foundation to build on. That’s Christ. Then we have the little flat pieces that start off the building with. That’s the apostles and prophets. Then there’s the rest of the pieces that get added on top. In the same way, God is building a people for Himself. They’re all knitted and locked together. Firmly situated on Christ. So, just as fellow citizens in a nation, and just as members of a family, and just as building blocks of a building, for those of us in Christ–that is, for those who turn from our sin and trust in God for salvation–we now stand unified. Implications of this Unity (4:1-3) So what does this mean for us? For us who, by faith, are members of God’s people now, what does it mean for us to be unified? There are numerous implications, but let me submit just one to you this morning. Look with me to chapter 4 verse 1. Therefore I, the prisoner for the Lord, urge you to walk worthy of the calling you have received, with all humility and gentleness, with patience accepting one another in love, diligently keeping the unity of the Spirit with the peace that binds us. [Ephesians 4:1-3] For us who are unified in Christ, we are commanded to strive for deeper unity. We are called to labor for this peace. Specifically regarding racial tension, this means recognizing inequality around us. It means recognizing privileges that one group might have over another. Brothers and sisters, we cannot simply be color-blind. Now, here me. I am by no means saying that we should hold stigmas or stereotypes against people. What I’m saying is that, in order for us to follow this command to keep unity and accept one another in love, we have to recognize the lives of our brothers and sisters who are of a different race. For example, I have an African-American friend–one of the friendliest guys you’ll ever meet. He served in the Marines, so he’s this really big, tough-looking guy, but he’s also in band and he wants to be a weather man, so he’s kind of like a teddy bear. But he was telling me how, at one point in his teenage years, that his father sat him down, and very seriously told him that he’s going to be treated differently. That simply because of his skin color, he’s going to have to live with the baggage of the stereotype that existed. He was going to have a difficult time with police, he’s going to intimidate people, and so on. Brothers and sisters, if we’re going to strive for deeper unity–if we’re truly going to accept one another in love, we must understand the lives that our brothers and sisters live. We have to understand the privilege we might have of not worrying how the police might treat us or not worrying that we might intimidate some lady that we’re passing on the street. We can’t just understand these things, but we have to be advocates to put these things away. We have to advocate for not just equality in treatment, but equality in privilege. Friends, this won’t be easy. It takes a lot of effort. Therefore I, the prisoner for the Lord, urge you to walk worthy of the calling you have received, with all humility and gentleness, with patience accepting one another in love, diligently keeping the unity of the Spirit with the peace that binds us. [Ephesians 4:1-3] Paul front-loads this command with a lot of phrases. He mentions, humility, gentleness, patience, and diligence. Brothers and sisters, this labor will be long and hard, but as unified members of God’s household, this labor is worth it. Christ did not leave us divide. He sought His people, died for them on the cross, and reconciling both to God in one body. A body that now exists in part, on earth today. If we are to follow our Lord, we must cherish our unified hope, and seek deeper unity. But let me remind you, we will not have perfect unity on this earth. Our hope is heaven where, as Revelation 7 tells, us, After this I looked, and there was a vast multitude from every nation, tribe, people, and language, which no one could number, standing before the throne and before the Lamb. They were robed in white with palm branches in their hands. And they cried out in a loud voice: Salvation belongs to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb! [Revelation 7:9-10] Let’s pray. Closing Prayer GREAT GOD, You created the heavens and the earth. We come before You, thanking You for Your Word. May we now respond with our lives. We long for the day when we will be gathered with the diverse multitude and declare: Salvation belongs to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb. Until then, may we seek unity amidst racial diversity in our communities, but especially in the Church, Your body, Your bride. We know we cannot do this on our own, so we humble petition You. May it be so. We ask in Christ’s name, Amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trinitarian Prayer Before Worship</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/prayers/2018/01/07/trinitarian-prayer-before-worship.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trinitarian Prayer Before Worship" /><published>2018-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/prayers/2018/01/07/trinitarian-prayer-before-worship</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/prayers/2018/01/07/trinitarian-prayer-before-worship.html">&lt;h4&gt;Entering A Place of Worship&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;GOD OF ALL GLORY,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;We gather to worship You by meeting with You through song, hearing and learning from Your Word, and responding with our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Father, by Your grace, You’ve given us Your Word. Every good and perfect gift is from above and among the chiefest is Your Word. Perfect, and infallible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Word Made Flesh, be our focus, and our glory. Let us remember Your righteous life, loving sacrifice, and mighty resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Spirit of God, You breathed life into us in salvation, and this same breath lives in this Word. Empower me to teach and others to hear. Let us respond in obedience, trust, and delight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;I ask this for Your glory among all people, forever and ever, amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">Entering A Place of Worship GOD OF ALL GLORY, We gather to worship You by meeting with You through song, hearing and learning from Your Word, and responding with our lives. Father, by Your grace, You’ve given us Your Word. Every good and perfect gift is from above and among the chiefest is Your Word. Perfect, and infallible. Word Made Flesh, be our focus, and our glory. Let us remember Your righteous life, loving sacrifice, and mighty resurrection. Spirit of God, You breathed life into us in salvation, and this same breath lives in this Word. Empower me to teach and others to hear. Let us respond in obedience, trust, and delight. I ask this for Your glory among all people, forever and ever, amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does God Keep His Promises?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/messages/2017/12/31/does-god-keep-his-promises.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does God Keep His Promises?" /><published>2017-12-31T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-12-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/messages/2017/12/31/does-god-keep-his-promises</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/messages/2017/12/31/does-god-keep-his-promises.html">&lt;p&gt;Prayer
GREAT FATHER,
Thank You for Your Word. It’s Your very breath, so we hold it precious to us.
With it, You mend our broken hearts, restore our dirtied souls, and rest our weary selves. Let us learn from it now, as You work to teach through me, and to apply it us. Help this weak man, teach Your mighty Word, Amen.
Sermon
If you’ve been with us the past few weeks you’ll know that we’re in a series looking at the different characters surrounding the birth of Christ. We’ve looked at Mary, the Shepherds, and Herod, and now we find ourselves looking at Simeon in Luke chapter 2.
As I was reflecting on this past year, in some ways, it felt like it passed quickly. But as I thought more, I realized just how much had happened in this year. Our new president was inaugurated, all of the unrest that came with that change, and even the guilty pleas of illegal activities surrounding his campaign.
The great tension between the United States and North Korea, and the intensifying contest of missile testing and political rhetoric.
The massacres in Las Vegas and Texas leaving so many families and communities devastated, while others began to question their own security from more events like this. Terrorist attacks all across Europe. Hurricanes absolutely obliterating cities and entire islands.
So much in our world is changing and shifting. The non-Christian looks at all of these things and asks: how can anything be stable? Is there anywhere I can rest on? Is there anything I can really rely on?
The Christian looks at all of these events and has to answer a similar question: How are we supposed to rest in God in this? Does God really keep His promises?
So as we look at Simeon in Luke chapter 2, let us keep these questions in mind: Does God keep His promises? And if God does keep His promises, can we rest securely on those promises?
So, I invite you to look with me to Luke chapter 2, verses 25 through 35.
Now there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon, and this man was righteous and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him. And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord’s Christ. And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the Law, he took him up in his arms and blessed God and said,
“Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word; for my eyes have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.”
And his father and his mother marveled at what was said about him. And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed (and a sword will pierce through your own soul also), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.”
So, with the question in mind, “does God keep his promises,” I want us to notice two main ideas. The first is that God kept his promise and the second is how God intended to fulfill His promise.
God Kept His Promise
So, to the first point, notice that God kept his promise.
Verse 25 opens with a description of a man named Simeon. There’s not a whole lot of information on Him. He appears briefly. He shows up here in verse 25. And after verse 35, Simeon isn’t talked about anymore. Inside of these short ten verses, all the biographical data we’re given is that he just happened to be in Jerusalem. As far as his character, we know that he was a righteous and devout man. Righteous in his dealings with people, and devout in his dealings with God. However, there’s one unique fact about Simeon that helps us with our question of whether or not God keeps His promises. Look at verse 26.
26 And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord’s Christ.
So God told Simeon that, before he dies, he would see the Messiah. But what did Simeon do with that promise? Verse 25 tells us that he waited. He looked forward to it.
One on the primary lessons that the Advent season teaches is the necessity of waiting. We don’t know how long Simeon had been waiting. It could have been days, weeks, months, years, even his entire life, but God’s people had been waiting on this promise for centuries.
They had been waiting from almost the beginning of time for a Savior that God had promised. Since the fall of Adam and Eve in the garden–the first sin of man–God had promised a Savior that would descend from Eve and redeem them. God’s people anticipated and longed for God’s promise to be fulfilled. Eve’s reactions to both Cain’s and Seth’s birth in Genesis 4 showed she was looking for the seed to bruise the serpents head that God promised in Genesis 3. She knew the Savior would be a descendent of hers, so she looked at each of them with great anticipation, but the Lord required her to wait.
Then, in Genesis 5, when Noah’s father reacted to His birth, he showed that he was looking forward to the same promise. Don’t turn there, but listen to Genesis,
29 “Out of the ground that the LORD has cursed, this one shall bring us relief from our work and from the painful toil of our hands.”
Noah’s father was looking forward to the fulfillment of God’s promise, and he hoped his son would be able to restore the land that was cursed since the sin of man in the garden, but he had to wait.
We can look and see that God promised His comfort through His prophets. Through Isaiah, He said,
Comfort, comfort my people, says your God. [Isaiah 40:1]
Then, through Jeremiah, He said,
Behold, I will gather them from all the countries to which I drove them in my anger and my wrath and in great indignation. I will bring them back to this place, and I will make them dwell in safety. And they shall be my people, and I will be their God. [Jeremiah 32:37-38]
During Jesus’s ministry, even He made the comment,
“Many prophets and righteous people longed to see the things you see yet didn’t see them; to hear the things that you hear yet didn’t hear them.” [Matthew 13:17]
God made His promise to His people, but they had to wait. Throughout the Bible, God’s people longed to see this promise fulfilled, and slowly but surely, God revealed the fulfillment of His promise.
Simeon’s short story in the Scriptures is right in the transition between waiting, and seeing. Up until this point many people had been longing to see the Messiah, but Simeon, by God’s grace, was promised that he would eventually see him before death.
Just to make a quick comment about this, isn’t it remarkable how long God’s people were made to wait? At the same time, isn’t it fascinating how short of a time we wait before we become disinterested with a promise? Let me just quickly encourage you. As you’ll see, many people in Scripture waited. God’s intentions in waiting are for our holiness. Lean into waiting and lean into the pursuit of holiness.
Simeon Was Led To The Promise
But, like I said, Simeon was promised by God that he would see the Messiah. So let’s see if God stayed true to His word. Look at verses 27.
And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the Law, he took him up in his arms and blessed God… [Luke 2:27-28]
Peculiar, isn’t it? It wasn’t as if Simeon had heard of this baby Jesus and came to meet Him. It wasn’t as if the shepherds’ news from the month before had caused Simeon to be interested in this particular baby. But the Scripture says, “Simeon came in the Spirit into the temple”.
At the same time, Joseph and Mary were just carrying out their lives. They followed the custom of the law to have Jesus circumcised on the 8th day after his birth, and they were in the process of going to both dedicate their firstborn son (according to the law) and offer sacrifices to purify Mary (according to the law).
And what was the result of this divine appointment? God fulfilled His promise to Simeon, and revealed that He had kept His promise to His people.
Look at verse 28 again.
…he took him up in his arms and blessed God and said, “Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word; for my eyes have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” [Luke 2:28-32]
God promised that Simeon would see the Messiah, and God kept His promise. Simeon longed to see the Christ, and Simeon saw Him.
Simeon Saw The Christ
It reminds me of a kid around Christmas time. They know that Christmas means presents. One day, they see their parent put up a Christmas tree and they know that the tree is a sign–a promise–that Christmas is soon. But, there are no presents are under it. The kid goes to bed, wakes up, checks the tree; no presents. Brushes their teeth, checks the tree; no presents. Goes to school, comes home, checks the tree; no presents. They go on for weeks. Eventually, one morning, Christmas morning, they wake up, peak around the corner to check the tree one more time, and as they lay eyes on their gift, they’re filled with excitement and joy.
Friends, in a much, much greater sense, this is Simeon. Notice this, many people were more than likely around. In fact, Jesus probably wasn’t even the only baby that was there to be dedicated that day. But out of all of these people, Simeon, filled with the Spirit, saw the Christ, the promise of God, and was filled with peace.
Simeon Received Peace
Now, pay attention this, Simeon saw the incarnate God, and had peace. He saw the Son of God, and had the peace of God. How can this be? Lots of people saw this baby, but none of them are described as having peace. Simeon, by the power of the Spirit, was able to see Christ with spiritual eyes, and recognize Him as the Messiah.
Matthew Henry meditated on it this way, “the eye is not satisfied with seeing, till it [has] see Christ, and then it is [satisfied].”
Ecclesiastes tells us,
the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing. [Ecclesiastes 1:8]
But, here we see Simeon, his eyes filled with the Christ, and finally satisfied with seeing.
Hear the command in Psalm 34:8,
“Taste and See the Lord is good. Blessed is the man who takes refuge in Him.”
We aren’t commanded to just acknowledge with our minds that the Lord is good. We are commanded, look! See! Savor! The Lord is good. He is precious and delightful, full of pleasures forevermore.
Friends, if you don’t see Christ this way, I urge you, look! Pray that God would show you. Gaze upon Him, in all of His glory, in all of His majesty and perfection. Treasure Him. Delight in Him. Turn away from whatever pleasures you’re holding onto and embrace the eternal pleasures of God, just as Simeon embrace this baby Jesus.
Look at verse 28. Simeon said, “now, I can go in peace” implying that before, he didn’t have peace. Let me ask this: why might Simeon not have peace? Remember verse 25. Simeon was a righteous and devout man. Why might a righteous and devout man not have peace?
Paul answers this in Romans chapter 3 when he says,
What then? Are we Jews any better off? No, not at all. For we have already charged that all, both Jews and Greeks, are under sin, as it is written: “None is righteous, no, not one; no one understands; no one seeks for God. [Romans 3:9-11]
So we see, Simeon may have been righteous in man’s eyes, but failed to meet God’s perfect righteousness. This is why Simeon looked forward to God’s promise of a Savior.
You see, God didn’t only fulfill His promise to Simeon–that Simeon would see the Christ–God also fulfilled His promise of salvation to His people. He did this by sending His Son the die in our place. Christ made peace through the blood of His cross. You don’t have to turn to it, but hear Romans 5:1,
Therefore, since we have been justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ. [Romans 5:1]
Friends, the only way we for us to stand before a holy God, is to be holy. But for us to be holy, something has to happen with our sin. If God is just, sin must be punished.
This is the beauty of the gospel. God has come, lived a perfect life that we could not live, took the penalty for our sin on the cross, and rose to prove that all of our sins were paid for, and we may freely come to Him in faith.
If you’re not a believer in Christ, you may have grown up in church your entire life, but let me urge you, unless you turn from your sin and trying to justify yourself, you face eternal wrath.
Simeon saw the promise of God fulfilled. He saw the Messiah and treasured Him. One old hymn says it well,
I hear the words of love – I gaze upon the blood – I see the mighty sacrifice – and I have peace with God
Friend, the only means of true peace, is the peace of God through Jesus Christ. God has kept His promise and offered salvation to us.
This Salvation is Offered to All
It doesn’t end there. Look with me at verse 32. Understand, this salvation isn’t offered to just a certain group of people.
…a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” [Luke 2:32]
Friends, this salvation is offered to each and every person. Every social class, every nation, every ethnicity, every language. Not one person is left out from this offer of peace. Not one.
That’s why it’s so heart-breaking that out of the 7 billion people in the world, 2 billion of them have little to no access to the gospel. It’s a reality for these people that they will born, live, die, and never hear the gospel. Most of them will never even meet a Christian who can teach them the gospel.
That’s why it’s so important for us to take international mission so seriously. God has offered salvation to all people and commanded us to teach the gospel to all. That’s why we give freely to Lottie Moon to support the International Missions Board. That’s why we give to the Southern Baptist Convention to help support Seminaries that help to train missionaries and pastors who will labor to advance God’s kingdom. That’s why we pray, fervently, that God would raise up workers to go and teach the gospel to the nations. We don’t just put the names of missionaries at the bottom of our bulletins for looks. They are there to remind us to constantly intercede on their behalf. Not just for safety, we pray that they would be met with a field prepared for harvest by God, and that God would establish and build healthy local churches to carry on His mission.
But we shouldn’t neglect our neighbors either. If the gospel is for all people, they’re included. Maybe that’s something the Lord’s convicted you about. If that’s so, let me encourage you, there are brothers and sisters here who are members of Salem and would be glad to encourage you and help you in that discipline.
Maybe you could walk across the street, or down the road, and invite a neighbor to dinner. Build a relationship with them. Learn about them. Ask them about their faith. Begin to teach the gospel through seeds of truth. And, hopefully, as the Lord wills, they will turn and trust in Christ.
So, we’ve seen that God kept His promise to Simeon. Although, even more importantly, He has kept His promise of salvation, and offered it to all people. But what does it look like for God to keep that promise?
How God Intends to Keep His Promise
I want us to notice how God intends to keep His promise through Jesus. Look at verse 34 and 35.
34 And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed
35 (and a sword will pierce through your own soul), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.”
We see here something of the cost that God has paid to fulfill His promise. We see the great torture that Christ has to endure to save His people. Two main points are mentioned in these verses: the certainty of Christ’s sacrifice and the ends (intent, results) of Christ’s sacrifice.
To address the first point, we see that God has appointed His Son to be the sacrifice. What does this mean that this child is appointed for something? Turn with me, to Acts chapter 4.
In this, the apostles Peter and John had just been arrested and interrogated for healing a man on the sabbath in the name of Jesus. When they are released, they are threatened not to speak in Christ’s name anymore.
So, when they get back to the other followers, they join together and pray, but notice what they pray in verse 27. They’re praising God and say,
…for truly in this city there were gathered together against your holy servant Jesus, whom you anointed, both Herod and Pontius Pilate, along with the Gentiles and the peoples of Israel, to do whatever your hand and your plan had predestined to take place. [Acts 4:27]
We see here, very clearly, that God had planned the condemnation of His son. He planned to use the evil of Herod and Pontius Pilate, and everyone else, to condemn the blameless Messiah.
Friends, God’s sovereignty is not a problem for us to solve, it’s a truth that we are given to rest in. As we see here, it’s the foundation of the salvation that God has provided. It’s essential to Him keeping His promise. It wasn’t that some rulers were out of control and killed the living God. God wielded their hatred to offer His Son as a sacrifice. Proverbs tell us,
The king’s heart is a stream of water in the hand of the Lord; he turns it wherever he will. [Proverbs 21:1]
God, in His sovereignty, planned to use the evil hearts of the rulers so that Christ would be delivered once, for all the saints. (Hebrews 10:10)
This gives us a powerful confidence in facing a changing world. Knowing that we rest in God who exercises absolute control over it, gives us a supreme hope. We don’t have to worry about the outcome of different political decisions, or the up-and-down trends of the stock market, or even potential threats of natural disaster. We rest in the confidence that we serve a God who is in total control and directs all things according His will, for our ultimate good.
Furthermore, God’s sovereignty gives us boldness in teaching the gospel. Look at verse 29 in Acts 4.
And now, Lord, look upon their threats and grant to your servants to continue to speak your word with all boldness… [Acts 4:29]
These followers had just been arrested, beaten, and threatened. They were surely, rightfully, terrified. But, they prayed fervently that God would embolden them as they remembered His absolute control over even the most cruel moment in history.
Maybe you struggle with the nervousness that come with sharing the gospel with a co-worker, or a family member. Let this truth encourage you. Let your rest be in God’s total control, and gladly share the gospel with all.
The Purpose of Christ’s Condemnation
So lastly, back in Luke 2, not only has God appointed His Son to be condemned, but, He has done so for a distinct purpose. Look at verse 34 and 35 again.
And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed (and a sword will pierce through your own soul also), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.” [Luke 2:34-35]
Christ has come for two distinct purposes. Christ came for the condemnation of many, and the salvation of others. He is both the aroma of life to some, and the aroma of life to other. He is foolishness to some, but wisdom to others. He is weakness to world, yet power to His saints. A stumbling block to many, but a way of salvation to others. He is a sign to be spoken against by some, but admired by others.
So what was the intention of Christ’s sacrifice? Verse 35 tells us it was to reveal the thoughts of many hearts. To whom are these intentions revealed? Our hearts are open and exposed to God who made all things, knows all things, and judges all things according to His perfect righteousness.
Maybe you’re here at church, today, to try to do your best and hope to earn your way to God’s favor. Don’t you see, we can’t retract back and hope that God can’t really see our hearts. We can’t hope that He sees the good things we do and forgets the deep darkness of our hearts. Each of us knows ourselves and we know the evil in our hearts. We may try to forget it, but we can’t go a day without it showing itself.
This is why me must rest in the gospel. This is why we turn from trying to justify ourselves, and turn to Christ. This is why we rejoice in the knowledge that even though the world shifts and changes, we have a God who keeps His promises. Namely, that we have a God who promised salvation to His people, and endured the cross to save us, if only we’d turn from our sin and trust in Him.
Let’s pray.
Prayer
LORD,
We thank you again, for Your word, and we thank you that You keep Your promises. You are perfectly faithful to keep them, and perfectly powerful to accomplish them.
By this truth and Your Spirit, let us be bold in the face of uncertainty, waiting patiently in trial, teaching the gospel to all, so that You may be magnified.
We ask this in Christ’s precious name, Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">Prayer GREAT FATHER, Thank You for Your Word. It’s Your very breath, so we hold it precious to us. With it, You mend our broken hearts, restore our dirtied souls, and rest our weary selves. Let us learn from it now, as You work to teach through me, and to apply it us. Help this weak man, teach Your mighty Word, Amen. Sermon If you’ve been with us the past few weeks you’ll know that we’re in a series looking at the different characters surrounding the birth of Christ. We’ve looked at Mary, the Shepherds, and Herod, and now we find ourselves looking at Simeon in Luke chapter 2. As I was reflecting on this past year, in some ways, it felt like it passed quickly. But as I thought more, I realized just how much had happened in this year. Our new president was inaugurated, all of the unrest that came with that change, and even the guilty pleas of illegal activities surrounding his campaign. The great tension between the United States and North Korea, and the intensifying contest of missile testing and political rhetoric. The massacres in Las Vegas and Texas leaving so many families and communities devastated, while others began to question their own security from more events like this. Terrorist attacks all across Europe. Hurricanes absolutely obliterating cities and entire islands. So much in our world is changing and shifting. The non-Christian looks at all of these things and asks: how can anything be stable? Is there anywhere I can rest on? Is there anything I can really rely on? The Christian looks at all of these events and has to answer a similar question: How are we supposed to rest in God in this? Does God really keep His promises? So as we look at Simeon in Luke chapter 2, let us keep these questions in mind: Does God keep His promises? And if God does keep His promises, can we rest securely on those promises? So, I invite you to look with me to Luke chapter 2, verses 25 through 35. Now there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon, and this man was righteous and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him. And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord’s Christ. And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the Law, he took him up in his arms and blessed God and said, “Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word; for my eyes have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” And his father and his mother marveled at what was said about him. And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed (and a sword will pierce through your own soul also), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.” So, with the question in mind, “does God keep his promises,” I want us to notice two main ideas. The first is that God kept his promise and the second is how God intended to fulfill His promise. God Kept His Promise So, to the first point, notice that God kept his promise. Verse 25 opens with a description of a man named Simeon. There’s not a whole lot of information on Him. He appears briefly. He shows up here in verse 25. And after verse 35, Simeon isn’t talked about anymore. Inside of these short ten verses, all the biographical data we’re given is that he just happened to be in Jerusalem. As far as his character, we know that he was a righteous and devout man. Righteous in his dealings with people, and devout in his dealings with God. However, there’s one unique fact about Simeon that helps us with our question of whether or not God keeps His promises. Look at verse 26. 26 And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord’s Christ. So God told Simeon that, before he dies, he would see the Messiah. But what did Simeon do with that promise? Verse 25 tells us that he waited. He looked forward to it. One on the primary lessons that the Advent season teaches is the necessity of waiting. We don’t know how long Simeon had been waiting. It could have been days, weeks, months, years, even his entire life, but God’s people had been waiting on this promise for centuries. They had been waiting from almost the beginning of time for a Savior that God had promised. Since the fall of Adam and Eve in the garden–the first sin of man–God had promised a Savior that would descend from Eve and redeem them. God’s people anticipated and longed for God’s promise to be fulfilled. Eve’s reactions to both Cain’s and Seth’s birth in Genesis 4 showed she was looking for the seed to bruise the serpents head that God promised in Genesis 3. She knew the Savior would be a descendent of hers, so she looked at each of them with great anticipation, but the Lord required her to wait. Then, in Genesis 5, when Noah’s father reacted to His birth, he showed that he was looking forward to the same promise. Don’t turn there, but listen to Genesis, 29 “Out of the ground that the LORD has cursed, this one shall bring us relief from our work and from the painful toil of our hands.” Noah’s father was looking forward to the fulfillment of God’s promise, and he hoped his son would be able to restore the land that was cursed since the sin of man in the garden, but he had to wait. We can look and see that God promised His comfort through His prophets. Through Isaiah, He said, Comfort, comfort my people, says your God. [Isaiah 40:1] Then, through Jeremiah, He said, Behold, I will gather them from all the countries to which I drove them in my anger and my wrath and in great indignation. I will bring them back to this place, and I will make them dwell in safety. And they shall be my people, and I will be their God. [Jeremiah 32:37-38] During Jesus’s ministry, even He made the comment, “Many prophets and righteous people longed to see the things you see yet didn’t see them; to hear the things that you hear yet didn’t hear them.” [Matthew 13:17] God made His promise to His people, but they had to wait. Throughout the Bible, God’s people longed to see this promise fulfilled, and slowly but surely, God revealed the fulfillment of His promise. Simeon’s short story in the Scriptures is right in the transition between waiting, and seeing. Up until this point many people had been longing to see the Messiah, but Simeon, by God’s grace, was promised that he would eventually see him before death. Just to make a quick comment about this, isn’t it remarkable how long God’s people were made to wait? At the same time, isn’t it fascinating how short of a time we wait before we become disinterested with a promise? Let me just quickly encourage you. As you’ll see, many people in Scripture waited. God’s intentions in waiting are for our holiness. Lean into waiting and lean into the pursuit of holiness. Simeon Was Led To The Promise But, like I said, Simeon was promised by God that he would see the Messiah. So let’s see if God stayed true to His word. Look at verses 27. And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the Law, he took him up in his arms and blessed God… [Luke 2:27-28] Peculiar, isn’t it? It wasn’t as if Simeon had heard of this baby Jesus and came to meet Him. It wasn’t as if the shepherds’ news from the month before had caused Simeon to be interested in this particular baby. But the Scripture says, “Simeon came in the Spirit into the temple”. At the same time, Joseph and Mary were just carrying out their lives. They followed the custom of the law to have Jesus circumcised on the 8th day after his birth, and they were in the process of going to both dedicate their firstborn son (according to the law) and offer sacrifices to purify Mary (according to the law). And what was the result of this divine appointment? God fulfilled His promise to Simeon, and revealed that He had kept His promise to His people. Look at verse 28 again. …he took him up in his arms and blessed God and said, “Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word; for my eyes have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” [Luke 2:28-32] God promised that Simeon would see the Messiah, and God kept His promise. Simeon longed to see the Christ, and Simeon saw Him. Simeon Saw The Christ It reminds me of a kid around Christmas time. They know that Christmas means presents. One day, they see their parent put up a Christmas tree and they know that the tree is a sign–a promise–that Christmas is soon. But, there are no presents are under it. The kid goes to bed, wakes up, checks the tree; no presents. Brushes their teeth, checks the tree; no presents. Goes to school, comes home, checks the tree; no presents. They go on for weeks. Eventually, one morning, Christmas morning, they wake up, peak around the corner to check the tree one more time, and as they lay eyes on their gift, they’re filled with excitement and joy. Friends, in a much, much greater sense, this is Simeon. Notice this, many people were more than likely around. In fact, Jesus probably wasn’t even the only baby that was there to be dedicated that day. But out of all of these people, Simeon, filled with the Spirit, saw the Christ, the promise of God, and was filled with peace. Simeon Received Peace Now, pay attention this, Simeon saw the incarnate God, and had peace. He saw the Son of God, and had the peace of God. How can this be? Lots of people saw this baby, but none of them are described as having peace. Simeon, by the power of the Spirit, was able to see Christ with spiritual eyes, and recognize Him as the Messiah. Matthew Henry meditated on it this way, “the eye is not satisfied with seeing, till it [has] see Christ, and then it is [satisfied].” Ecclesiastes tells us, the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing. [Ecclesiastes 1:8] But, here we see Simeon, his eyes filled with the Christ, and finally satisfied with seeing. Hear the command in Psalm 34:8, “Taste and See the Lord is good. Blessed is the man who takes refuge in Him.” We aren’t commanded to just acknowledge with our minds that the Lord is good. We are commanded, look! See! Savor! The Lord is good. He is precious and delightful, full of pleasures forevermore. Friends, if you don’t see Christ this way, I urge you, look! Pray that God would show you. Gaze upon Him, in all of His glory, in all of His majesty and perfection. Treasure Him. Delight in Him. Turn away from whatever pleasures you’re holding onto and embrace the eternal pleasures of God, just as Simeon embrace this baby Jesus. Look at verse 28. Simeon said, “now, I can go in peace” implying that before, he didn’t have peace. Let me ask this: why might Simeon not have peace? Remember verse 25. Simeon was a righteous and devout man. Why might a righteous and devout man not have peace? Paul answers this in Romans chapter 3 when he says, What then? Are we Jews any better off? No, not at all. For we have already charged that all, both Jews and Greeks, are under sin, as it is written: “None is righteous, no, not one; no one understands; no one seeks for God. [Romans 3:9-11] So we see, Simeon may have been righteous in man’s eyes, but failed to meet God’s perfect righteousness. This is why Simeon looked forward to God’s promise of a Savior. You see, God didn’t only fulfill His promise to Simeon–that Simeon would see the Christ–God also fulfilled His promise of salvation to His people. He did this by sending His Son the die in our place. Christ made peace through the blood of His cross. You don’t have to turn to it, but hear Romans 5:1, Therefore, since we have been justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ. [Romans 5:1] Friends, the only way we for us to stand before a holy God, is to be holy. But for us to be holy, something has to happen with our sin. If God is just, sin must be punished. This is the beauty of the gospel. God has come, lived a perfect life that we could not live, took the penalty for our sin on the cross, and rose to prove that all of our sins were paid for, and we may freely come to Him in faith. If you’re not a believer in Christ, you may have grown up in church your entire life, but let me urge you, unless you turn from your sin and trying to justify yourself, you face eternal wrath. Simeon saw the promise of God fulfilled. He saw the Messiah and treasured Him. One old hymn says it well, I hear the words of love – I gaze upon the blood – I see the mighty sacrifice – and I have peace with God Friend, the only means of true peace, is the peace of God through Jesus Christ. God has kept His promise and offered salvation to us. This Salvation is Offered to All It doesn’t end there. Look with me at verse 32. Understand, this salvation isn’t offered to just a certain group of people. …a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” [Luke 2:32] Friends, this salvation is offered to each and every person. Every social class, every nation, every ethnicity, every language. Not one person is left out from this offer of peace. Not one. That’s why it’s so heart-breaking that out of the 7 billion people in the world, 2 billion of them have little to no access to the gospel. It’s a reality for these people that they will born, live, die, and never hear the gospel. Most of them will never even meet a Christian who can teach them the gospel. That’s why it’s so important for us to take international mission so seriously. God has offered salvation to all people and commanded us to teach the gospel to all. That’s why we give freely to Lottie Moon to support the International Missions Board. That’s why we give to the Southern Baptist Convention to help support Seminaries that help to train missionaries and pastors who will labor to advance God’s kingdom. That’s why we pray, fervently, that God would raise up workers to go and teach the gospel to the nations. We don’t just put the names of missionaries at the bottom of our bulletins for looks. They are there to remind us to constantly intercede on their behalf. Not just for safety, we pray that they would be met with a field prepared for harvest by God, and that God would establish and build healthy local churches to carry on His mission. But we shouldn’t neglect our neighbors either. If the gospel is for all people, they’re included. Maybe that’s something the Lord’s convicted you about. If that’s so, let me encourage you, there are brothers and sisters here who are members of Salem and would be glad to encourage you and help you in that discipline. Maybe you could walk across the street, or down the road, and invite a neighbor to dinner. Build a relationship with them. Learn about them. Ask them about their faith. Begin to teach the gospel through seeds of truth. And, hopefully, as the Lord wills, they will turn and trust in Christ. So, we’ve seen that God kept His promise to Simeon. Although, even more importantly, He has kept His promise of salvation, and offered it to all people. But what does it look like for God to keep that promise? How God Intends to Keep His Promise I want us to notice how God intends to keep His promise through Jesus. Look at verse 34 and 35. 34 And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed 35 (and a sword will pierce through your own soul), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.” We see here something of the cost that God has paid to fulfill His promise. We see the great torture that Christ has to endure to save His people. Two main points are mentioned in these verses: the certainty of Christ’s sacrifice and the ends (intent, results) of Christ’s sacrifice. To address the first point, we see that God has appointed His Son to be the sacrifice. What does this mean that this child is appointed for something? Turn with me, to Acts chapter 4. In this, the apostles Peter and John had just been arrested and interrogated for healing a man on the sabbath in the name of Jesus. When they are released, they are threatened not to speak in Christ’s name anymore. So, when they get back to the other followers, they join together and pray, but notice what they pray in verse 27. They’re praising God and say, …for truly in this city there were gathered together against your holy servant Jesus, whom you anointed, both Herod and Pontius Pilate, along with the Gentiles and the peoples of Israel, to do whatever your hand and your plan had predestined to take place. [Acts 4:27] We see here, very clearly, that God had planned the condemnation of His son. He planned to use the evil of Herod and Pontius Pilate, and everyone else, to condemn the blameless Messiah. Friends, God’s sovereignty is not a problem for us to solve, it’s a truth that we are given to rest in. As we see here, it’s the foundation of the salvation that God has provided. It’s essential to Him keeping His promise. It wasn’t that some rulers were out of control and killed the living God. God wielded their hatred to offer His Son as a sacrifice. Proverbs tell us, The king’s heart is a stream of water in the hand of the Lord; he turns it wherever he will. [Proverbs 21:1] God, in His sovereignty, planned to use the evil hearts of the rulers so that Christ would be delivered once, for all the saints. (Hebrews 10:10) This gives us a powerful confidence in facing a changing world. Knowing that we rest in God who exercises absolute control over it, gives us a supreme hope. We don’t have to worry about the outcome of different political decisions, or the up-and-down trends of the stock market, or even potential threats of natural disaster. We rest in the confidence that we serve a God who is in total control and directs all things according His will, for our ultimate good. Furthermore, God’s sovereignty gives us boldness in teaching the gospel. Look at verse 29 in Acts 4. And now, Lord, look upon their threats and grant to your servants to continue to speak your word with all boldness… [Acts 4:29] These followers had just been arrested, beaten, and threatened. They were surely, rightfully, terrified. But, they prayed fervently that God would embolden them as they remembered His absolute control over even the most cruel moment in history. Maybe you struggle with the nervousness that come with sharing the gospel with a co-worker, or a family member. Let this truth encourage you. Let your rest be in God’s total control, and gladly share the gospel with all. The Purpose of Christ’s Condemnation So lastly, back in Luke 2, not only has God appointed His Son to be condemned, but, He has done so for a distinct purpose. Look at verse 34 and 35 again. And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed (and a sword will pierce through your own soul also), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.” [Luke 2:34-35] Christ has come for two distinct purposes. Christ came for the condemnation of many, and the salvation of others. He is both the aroma of life to some, and the aroma of life to other. He is foolishness to some, but wisdom to others. He is weakness to world, yet power to His saints. A stumbling block to many, but a way of salvation to others. He is a sign to be spoken against by some, but admired by others. So what was the intention of Christ’s sacrifice? Verse 35 tells us it was to reveal the thoughts of many hearts. To whom are these intentions revealed? Our hearts are open and exposed to God who made all things, knows all things, and judges all things according to His perfect righteousness. Maybe you’re here at church, today, to try to do your best and hope to earn your way to God’s favor. Don’t you see, we can’t retract back and hope that God can’t really see our hearts. We can’t hope that He sees the good things we do and forgets the deep darkness of our hearts. Each of us knows ourselves and we know the evil in our hearts. We may try to forget it, but we can’t go a day without it showing itself. This is why me must rest in the gospel. This is why we turn from trying to justify ourselves, and turn to Christ. This is why we rejoice in the knowledge that even though the world shifts and changes, we have a God who keeps His promises. Namely, that we have a God who promised salvation to His people, and endured the cross to save us, if only we’d turn from our sin and trust in Him. Let’s pray. Prayer LORD, We thank you again, for Your word, and we thank you that You keep Your promises. You are perfectly faithful to keep them, and perfectly powerful to accomplish them. By this truth and Your Spirit, let us be bold in the face of uncertainty, waiting patiently in trial, teaching the gospel to all, so that You may be magnified. We ask this in Christ’s precious name, Amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Lunchtime Prayer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/prayers/2017/12/29/a-lunchtime-prayer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Lunchtime Prayer" /><published>2017-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/prayers/2017/12/29/a-lunchtime-prayer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/prayers/2017/12/29/a-lunchtime-prayer.html">&lt;h4&gt;At a Lunchtime Meal&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;GREAT PROVIDER,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;You called me to rise once again this morning, to go out, to labor, to communicate, to learn, to study, to advance Your kingdom, to grow in holiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Now, I sit to enjoy this meal You’ve given me. By Your grace alone, I am able to sit here, to enjoy this food, to have my body restored with nourishment and grown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;This food doesn’t need flavors, nor does my tongue need taste. Yet You’ve richly blessed me with this gift. Let me enjoy this food. The flavors, the texture, to temperature. Let it remind me of You abundant goodness–the gifts that You’ve lavished me with, especially, the gift of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;His blood is the blood of the incarnate God–infinite in value. How great the cost of my sin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;O God, let me walk in humility, covered in Christ’s righteousness, being conformed to His likeness, rejoicing in the goodness and glory of Your gospel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">At a Lunchtime Meal GREAT PROVIDER, You called me to rise once again this morning, to go out, to labor, to communicate, to learn, to study, to advance Your kingdom, to grow in holiness. Now, I sit to enjoy this meal You’ve given me. By Your grace alone, I am able to sit here, to enjoy this food, to have my body restored with nourishment and grown. This food doesn’t need flavors, nor does my tongue need taste. Yet You’ve richly blessed me with this gift. Let me enjoy this food. The flavors, the texture, to temperature. Let it remind me of You abundant goodness–the gifts that You’ve lavished me with, especially, the gift of Christ. His blood is the blood of the incarnate God–infinite in value. How great the cost of my sin! O God, let me walk in humility, covered in Christ’s righteousness, being conformed to His likeness, rejoicing in the goodness and glory of Your gospel.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Light Dwells With Him</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/12/25/light-dwells-with-him.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Light Dwells With Him" /><published>2017-12-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-12-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/12/25/light-dwells-with-him</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/12/25/light-dwells-with-him.html">&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;What the king is asking is so difficult that no one can make it known to him except the gods, whose dwelling place is not with mortals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Daniel 2:11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening chapters of Daniel overflow with the God’s supremacy over all. Daniel and his friends were compelled to not eat the unclean food (1:8), but God granted them favor and compassion (1:9), and unnatural health (1:15). Daniel and his friends were trained for the king’s courts, and the Lord gave them superior knowledge and understanding (1:17,19). Over and over again, God displayed His multifaceted excellence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, in chapter two, God prepared an opportunity to display His supremacy further. The king has a dream. Now, he wants an interpretation, but he wants a true interpretation, so he keeps the dream secret and demands that his interpreters tell him his dream and the interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this task is certainly outside of man’s reach, but perfectly within God’s. The king’s usual interpreters recognize this, but with error. They say, &quot;how can we do this? Only gods can and they’re far away. There’s no way this can be done&quot; (2:11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement offers a challenge that fills out the display of God’s supremacy so far in Daniel. Yes, God is immeasurable in power and wisdom, but He is not remove from His people. He dwells with them. He is close by and intimately involved in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this statement, the king began to execute these men (who conspired to lie to him about the dream). Eventually, Daniel and his friends plead for the Lord to show mercy, and He reveals the dream and its interpretation to them. In response Daniel praises God. Notice this phrase in Daniel’s praise,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;He knows what is in the darkness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;and light dwells with Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Daniel 2:22&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God is supreme over all—light and dark, good and evil—yet, in His kindness, He’s came to dwell with darkness for a time, so that He may become darkness, and defeat it. He’s redeemed His people from darkness to light, from death to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The king’s dream, desire, and precautions. Daniel’s true interpretation and praise. All of these were orchestrated by God to bring glory to His name and good to His people. Take heart, God’s perfect and unwavering sovereignty and desire for His glory is a rock-solid foundation for our hope in salvation. This is the message of Christmas: we have a God who dwelled with us, so that His people may dwell with Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;GREAT GOD,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;May Your name be honored throughout all generations,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;You reign supreme over all. Nations and kings rise and fall at Your will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;None are wise, unless You, the Spring of All Wisdom and Knowledge, flows into them. None are powerful, unless You, the Great Builder, fortify and strengthen them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;In Your manifold perfections, You’ve exceeded all earthly understanding of Your glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;In Your goodness, You’ve judged our sin, but in Your mercy, You’ve judged it on Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;In Your grace, You’ve given us life and peace, if only we turn from our sin and trust in You.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;May we rest in the peace of Your absolute sovereignty, and tender intimacy. May Your word reign supreme in our lives, as we treasure Christ more fully. I ask this in His name, Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">What the king is asking is so difficult that no one can make it known to him except the gods, whose dwelling place is not with mortals. Daniel 2:11 The opening chapters of Daniel overflow with the God’s supremacy over all. Daniel and his friends were compelled to not eat the unclean food (1:8), but God granted them favor and compassion (1:9), and unnatural health (1:15). Daniel and his friends were trained for the king’s courts, and the Lord gave them superior knowledge and understanding (1:17,19). Over and over again, God displayed His multifaceted excellence. Again, in chapter two, God prepared an opportunity to display His supremacy further. The king has a dream. Now, he wants an interpretation, but he wants a true interpretation, so he keeps the dream secret and demands that his interpreters tell him his dream and the interpretation. Now, this task is certainly outside of man’s reach, but perfectly within God’s. The king’s usual interpreters recognize this, but with error. They say, &quot;how can we do this? Only gods can and they’re far away. There’s no way this can be done&quot; (2:11). This statement offers a challenge that fills out the display of God’s supremacy so far in Daniel. Yes, God is immeasurable in power and wisdom, but He is not remove from His people. He dwells with them. He is close by and intimately involved in their lives. After this statement, the king began to execute these men (who conspired to lie to him about the dream). Eventually, Daniel and his friends plead for the Lord to show mercy, and He reveals the dream and its interpretation to them. In response Daniel praises God. Notice this phrase in Daniel’s praise, He knows what is in the darkness and light dwells with Him. Daniel 2:22 God is supreme over all—light and dark, good and evil—yet, in His kindness, He’s came to dwell with darkness for a time, so that He may become darkness, and defeat it. He’s redeemed His people from darkness to light, from death to life. The king’s dream, desire, and precautions. Daniel’s true interpretation and praise. All of these were orchestrated by God to bring glory to His name and good to His people. Take heart, God’s perfect and unwavering sovereignty and desire for His glory is a rock-solid foundation for our hope in salvation. This is the message of Christmas: we have a God who dwelled with us, so that His people may dwell with Him. GREAT GOD, May Your name be honored throughout all generations, You reign supreme over all. Nations and kings rise and fall at Your will. None are wise, unless You, the Spring of All Wisdom and Knowledge, flows into them. None are powerful, unless You, the Great Builder, fortify and strengthen them. In Your manifold perfections, You’ve exceeded all earthly understanding of Your glory. In Your goodness, You’ve judged our sin, but in Your mercy, You’ve judged it on Christ. In Your grace, You’ve given us life and peace, if only we turn from our sin and trust in You. May we rest in the peace of Your absolute sovereignty, and tender intimacy. May Your word reign supreme in our lives, as we treasure Christ more fully. I ask this in His name, Amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">He Wields All</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/12/15/he-wields-all.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="He Wields All" /><published>2017-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/12/15/he-wields-all</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/12/15/he-wields-all.html">&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;1 In those days a decree went out from Caesar Augustus that all the world should be registered. 2 This was the first registration when Quirinius was governor of Syria. 3 And all went to be registered, each to his own town. 4 And Joseph also went up from Galilee, from the town of Nazareth, to Judea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and lineage of David, 5 to be registered with Mary, his betrothed, who was with child. 6 And while they were there, the time came for her to give birth. 7 And she gave birth to her firstborn son and wrapped him in swaddling cloths and laid him in a manger, because there was no place for them in the inn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Luke 2: 1-7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the circumstances in this story. Caesar Augustus declared a census. Mary was almost ready to give birth. Joseph (a descendent of David) betrothed Mary. God threaded all these together at the perfect time. He did this to fulfill His Word in Micah 5:2. Isn’t this peculiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a rich example of God’s sovereignty. Namely, that God pre-ordained these perfect circumstances. God put it in the heart of Caesar to conduct a census so that He would eventually redeem His people. We see that God wields mighty empires in His hands to glorify Himself. He controls the political powers of the world to bring immense joy to His people. Solomon spoke to this when he said,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;The king's heart is a stream of water in the hand of the Lord; he turns it wherever he will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Proverbs 21:1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned this past week that a few years ago, in a North African kingdom, an intense persecution broke out against the Church. Islam reigned in this country and they sought to exterminate everything else. The persecution was especially brutal for the native believers. They suffered well for the name of Christ. They proclaimed salvation in Christ alone throughout it all, but they suffered. This story is common in the world, and rightly inspires prayer for the persecuted Church. However, if we’re not careful, we can miss the beauty of God’s sovereign work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to this, most people in this country believed that it was impossible for Muslims to become Christians. Now, because of the mistreatment, slander, and so on, they are very aware that Muslims can, and have, become Christians. They are interested in these stories of conversion and are more open to hearing Gospel truths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story rings with the words of Joseph in Genesis 50:20,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;As for you, you meant evil against me, but God meant it for good, to bring it about that many people should be kept alive, as they are today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Genesis 50:20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we have an almighty God who exercises His authority over political powers and economic forces to sovereignly promote His glorious redemptive work. His ways are truly beyond our comprehension. He often employs suffering and hardship—that is, He sovereignly allows such events—to bring exceeding joy to His people and build His church. What the world—and its father, Satan—intend for destruction and pain, the Lord powerfully uses to give everlasting life and joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t this good news for us? That God is powerful over even the strongest of systems, and that He wields them in His hand to care even the smallest and most insignificant citizens of His kingdom. God orchestrated the entire Roman empire to move two nobodies 70 miles to a small dirty town outside of Jerusalem. Take heart, our King is mighty over all other kings. They will one day bow before Him, and we will have rest as we behold Christ’s glory. But, until then, let us hold to the faith with steadfast hope. Let us rest that all things are under Christ, our Lord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;ALMIGHTY GOD, You alone are worthy of worship. All else are idols. In the fullness of Your love, You have become truly man to bear the shame of many and redeem them on the cross. By Your death, many live. Hallelujah!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;FATHER, while this truth is great, so many have not heard, and so many are under persecution for this truth. They live under the oppression of Islam, in the darkness of a system that demands their fearful obedience to gain favor from a false god.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;O GOD, would You save them? Would You show them the depth of their sinful darkness and the bright glory of Your holiness? Let them mourn over the great gap between these two. But, God, in the next breath, breathe life into them. Let them rejoice in the knowledge that You have provided a righteousness that is not our own, but Christ’s. Let them treasure Him. Let them grow in love and faith. Let them persevere with the steadfast hope of their reward—the reward of beholding You throughout eternity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;I ask these things for Your glory by the mighty name of Christ, Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">1 In those days a decree went out from Caesar Augustus that all the world should be registered. 2 This was the first registration when Quirinius was governor of Syria. 3 And all went to be registered, each to his own town. 4 And Joseph also went up from Galilee, from the town of Nazareth, to Judea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and lineage of David, 5 to be registered with Mary, his betrothed, who was with child. 6 And while they were there, the time came for her to give birth. 7 And she gave birth to her firstborn son and wrapped him in swaddling cloths and laid him in a manger, because there was no place for them in the inn. Luke 2: 1-7 Consider the circumstances in this story. Caesar Augustus declared a census. Mary was almost ready to give birth. Joseph (a descendent of David) betrothed Mary. God threaded all these together at the perfect time. He did this to fulfill His Word in Micah 5:2. Isn’t this peculiar? This is a rich example of God’s sovereignty. Namely, that God pre-ordained these perfect circumstances. God put it in the heart of Caesar to conduct a census so that He would eventually redeem His people. We see that God wields mighty empires in His hands to glorify Himself. He controls the political powers of the world to bring immense joy to His people. Solomon spoke to this when he said, The king's heart is a stream of water in the hand of the Lord; he turns it wherever he will. Proverbs 21:1 I learned this past week that a few years ago, in a North African kingdom, an intense persecution broke out against the Church. Islam reigned in this country and they sought to exterminate everything else. The persecution was especially brutal for the native believers. They suffered well for the name of Christ. They proclaimed salvation in Christ alone throughout it all, but they suffered. This story is common in the world, and rightly inspires prayer for the persecuted Church. However, if we’re not careful, we can miss the beauty of God’s sovereign work. Prior to this, most people in this country believed that it was impossible for Muslims to become Christians. Now, because of the mistreatment, slander, and so on, they are very aware that Muslims can, and have, become Christians. They are interested in these stories of conversion and are more open to hearing Gospel truths. This story rings with the words of Joseph in Genesis 50:20, As for you, you meant evil against me, but God meant it for good, to bring it about that many people should be kept alive, as they are today. Genesis 50:20 Indeed, we have an almighty God who exercises His authority over political powers and economic forces to sovereignly promote His glorious redemptive work. His ways are truly beyond our comprehension. He often employs suffering and hardship—that is, He sovereignly allows such events—to bring exceeding joy to His people and build His church. What the world—and its father, Satan—intend for destruction and pain, the Lord powerfully uses to give everlasting life and joy. Isn’t this good news for us? That God is powerful over even the strongest of systems, and that He wields them in His hand to care even the smallest and most insignificant citizens of His kingdom. God orchestrated the entire Roman empire to move two nobodies 70 miles to a small dirty town outside of Jerusalem. Take heart, our King is mighty over all other kings. They will one day bow before Him, and we will have rest as we behold Christ’s glory. But, until then, let us hold to the faith with steadfast hope. Let us rest that all things are under Christ, our Lord. ALMIGHTY GOD, You alone are worthy of worship. All else are idols. In the fullness of Your love, You have become truly man to bear the shame of many and redeem them on the cross. By Your death, many live. Hallelujah! FATHER, while this truth is great, so many have not heard, and so many are under persecution for this truth. They live under the oppression of Islam, in the darkness of a system that demands their fearful obedience to gain favor from a false god. O GOD, would You save them? Would You show them the depth of their sinful darkness and the bright glory of Your holiness? Let them mourn over the great gap between these two. But, God, in the next breath, breathe life into them. Let them rejoice in the knowledge that You have provided a righteousness that is not our own, but Christ’s. Let them treasure Him. Let them grow in love and faith. Let them persevere with the steadfast hope of their reward—the reward of beholding You throughout eternity. I ask these things for Your glory by the mighty name of Christ, Amen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Broken and Clean</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/memorization/2017/11/25/broken-and-clean.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Broken and Clean" /><published>2017-11-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-11-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/memorization/2017/11/25/broken-and-clean</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/memorization/2017/11/25/broken-and-clean.html">&lt;h4&gt;An Advent Devotional for 2017&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Advent season officially begins on the fourth Sunday before Christmas and continues until Christmas Eve or Day. There are a variety of ways to celebrate Advent depending on tradition and background. One tradition is to use an Advent calendar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this resource and the anticipation of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../broken-and-clean/&quot;&gt;Just follow this link.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much love,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divine Joy&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">An Advent Devotional for 2017 The Advent season officially begins on the fourth Sunday before Christmas and continues until Christmas Eve or Day. There are a variety of ways to celebrate Advent depending on tradition and background. One tradition is to use an Advent calendar Enjoy this resource and the anticipation of Christ. Just follow this link. Much love, Divine Joy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Supreme Gift-Giver</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/11/20/the-supreme-gift-giver.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Supreme Gift-Giver" /><published>2017-11-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/11/20/the-supreme-gift-giver</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/devotions/2017/11/20/the-supreme-gift-giver.html">&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;&quot;Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights, with whom there is no variation or shadow due to change.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;James 1:17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently the Lord has profoundly deepened my understanding of His glory as it is revealed around us. Shadows or images are revealed throughout the Bible. The Passover lamb is a shadow of our truer and better Passover Lamb. The Exodus is a shadow of our truer and better deliverance from sin into the promised land of God’s eternal kingdom. Marriage between man and woman is a shadow of our truer and better union with Christ—being brought into joyful companionship with the Trinity. All of these (and more) use presently visible realities—realities that are to be enjoyed by us, thus glorifying God—to cast an image of divine wonders—wonder that magnify these truths to the infinite and perfect degree, thus glorifying God even more. This simultaneous stimulation of both our worldly and spiritual senses greatly deepens our satisfaction in all that God has provided us in our earthly sojourn. It shows both God’s present provision, and His heavenly gifts to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this is not where the Lord has stopped teaching me. Not only has He deepened my appreciation of these inspired images and shadows, but He’s opened my eyes to the wonder that surrounds me in all areas. Jonathan Edwards explained that the Bible’s use of images and shadows provide us with a framework to understand these images and shadows, and the Lord’s creation provides us with many other images and shadows to interpret with this framework. That is, the Bible provides us with a sort of grammar for images, while creation provides us with the words. While these images, unlike the biblically-provided ones, are uninspired and, therefore, not flawless, they can enhance our seeing and savoring Christ. With both, we unveil the mysteries of heaven in all that surrounds us. This could be as simple as seeing the joy and satisfaction in friendship, but understanding the eternally increasing and infinitely satisfying relationship with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve meditated on many of these recently, and the Lord has shown Himself sweeter and sweeter with each passing thought. However, I wanted to write to you about one of these specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than likely, you’ve heard of the 5 love languages. In case you haven’t, they are: Physical touch, quality time, words of affirmation, acts of service, and gift giving. I’ve had the most trouble with the last of these. I looked down on this means of affection as materialism-driven and woefully-depraved. However, I noticed today that God actually shows His love through gift giving. Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above (James 1:17), from God who gives generously (James 1:15). God lavished His church with many spiritual gifts (1 Corinthians 12:4). God has given faith to His people (Ephesians 2:8). Even the word for &quot;grace&quot;—that is lavished on His elect (Ephesians 1:8)—is derived from the word for &quot;gift&quot;. The pinnacle of this all is that God has given His son to redeem His rebellious children. (John 3:16) For me to slight the love language of gift giving is for me to defame the Supreme Gift Giver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding that God is the Supreme Gift Giver gives us a deep and calming assurance. Consider the hymn lyrics, &quot;come thou fount of every blessing.&quot; Or even the doxology, &quot;praise God from whom all blessings flow.&quot; These songs—and, I assure you, the praises of heaven also—are laced with language that recognizes and resounds with thankfulness towards God’s gift giving attributes. Furthermore, God doesn’t half-heartedly give good gifts to us. He delights in lavishing us with gifts. (Jeremiah 32:41) His whole heart and soul are involved in His giving. Now, God’s gift giving is primarily for His own delight in Himself, and this is not the letter to explain this matter, but understand that we are joyful and fortunate beneficiaries in God’s master plan to satisfy Himself in His glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for our lives though? What does it look like to live this out? This is where I so often fail. My heart is slow to learn and weak to put into motion these profound promises. If God is the Supreme Gift Giver, God delights in giving good gifts to His people, and all good gifts come from God, then we have great hope in our lives as we face each day. Even now, when I struggle with anxiousness regarding possibilities in the near future, I can rest in the knowledge that these possibilities, if they are truly good, will be given by God, from whom all blessings flow freely. I am also assured that, if these desires are not truly best, they won’t be given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, recognizing God as the Supreme Gift Giver causes deep rest in His children as they sojourn with a boundless optimism—an optimism that is buttressed by God’s sovereignty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;MOST HIGH GOD,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Your ways know no change. Your goodness knows no limit. Your love knows no end. You delight in lavishing Your people with good gifts. These gifts aren’t merely the fulfillment of our shallow materialistic cravings, but these gifts are the true and sure fulfillment of our soul’s deepest longings. To know You is our greatest joy, but our hearts are hard to change, our minds are slow to learn, and our flesh is weak to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Lord, according to Your vast mercy and steadfast love, give us a greater insight into this heavenly reality. Let us be overwhelmed with optimism as we rest in the promises You have given to us. Let us not be discouraged by doubt, but strengthen by the knowledge of Your goodness. Let us not be ravaged by unbelief, but empowered by confident hope that You sovereignly operate all things for Your maximum glory and our maximum good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;To You be all glory among all people through all generations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dylan Howard</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights, with whom there is no variation or shadow due to change.&quot; James 1:17 Recently the Lord has profoundly deepened my understanding of His glory as it is revealed around us. Shadows or images are revealed throughout the Bible. The Passover lamb is a shadow of our truer and better Passover Lamb. The Exodus is a shadow of our truer and better deliverance from sin into the promised land of God’s eternal kingdom. Marriage between man and woman is a shadow of our truer and better union with Christ—being brought into joyful companionship with the Trinity. All of these (and more) use presently visible realities—realities that are to be enjoyed by us, thus glorifying God—to cast an image of divine wonders—wonder that magnify these truths to the infinite and perfect degree, thus glorifying God even more. This simultaneous stimulation of both our worldly and spiritual senses greatly deepens our satisfaction in all that God has provided us in our earthly sojourn. It shows both God’s present provision, and His heavenly gifts to come. However, this is not where the Lord has stopped teaching me. Not only has He deepened my appreciation of these inspired images and shadows, but He’s opened my eyes to the wonder that surrounds me in all areas. Jonathan Edwards explained that the Bible’s use of images and shadows provide us with a framework to understand these images and shadows, and the Lord’s creation provides us with many other images and shadows to interpret with this framework. That is, the Bible provides us with a sort of grammar for images, while creation provides us with the words. While these images, unlike the biblically-provided ones, are uninspired and, therefore, not flawless, they can enhance our seeing and savoring Christ. With both, we unveil the mysteries of heaven in all that surrounds us. This could be as simple as seeing the joy and satisfaction in friendship, but understanding the eternally increasing and infinitely satisfying relationship with God. I’ve meditated on many of these recently, and the Lord has shown Himself sweeter and sweeter with each passing thought. However, I wanted to write to you about one of these specifically. More than likely, you’ve heard of the 5 love languages. In case you haven’t, they are: Physical touch, quality time, words of affirmation, acts of service, and gift giving. I’ve had the most trouble with the last of these. I looked down on this means of affection as materialism-driven and woefully-depraved. However, I noticed today that God actually shows His love through gift giving. Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above (James 1:17), from God who gives generously (James 1:15). God lavished His church with many spiritual gifts (1 Corinthians 12:4). God has given faith to His people (Ephesians 2:8). Even the word for &quot;grace&quot;—that is lavished on His elect (Ephesians 1:8)—is derived from the word for &quot;gift&quot;. The pinnacle of this all is that God has given His son to redeem His rebellious children. (John 3:16) For me to slight the love language of gift giving is for me to defame the Supreme Gift Giver. Understanding that God is the Supreme Gift Giver gives us a deep and calming assurance. Consider the hymn lyrics, &quot;come thou fount of every blessing.&quot; Or even the doxology, &quot;praise God from whom all blessings flow.&quot; These songs—and, I assure you, the praises of heaven also—are laced with language that recognizes and resounds with thankfulness towards God’s gift giving attributes. Furthermore, God doesn’t half-heartedly give good gifts to us. He delights in lavishing us with gifts. (Jeremiah 32:41) His whole heart and soul are involved in His giving. Now, God’s gift giving is primarily for His own delight in Himself, and this is not the letter to explain this matter, but understand that we are joyful and fortunate beneficiaries in God’s master plan to satisfy Himself in His glory. What does this mean for our lives though? What does it look like to live this out? This is where I so often fail. My heart is slow to learn and weak to put into motion these profound promises. If God is the Supreme Gift Giver, God delights in giving good gifts to His people, and all good gifts come from God, then we have great hope in our lives as we face each day. Even now, when I struggle with anxiousness regarding possibilities in the near future, I can rest in the knowledge that these possibilities, if they are truly good, will be given by God, from whom all blessings flow freely. I am also assured that, if these desires are not truly best, they won’t be given. In short, recognizing God as the Supreme Gift Giver causes deep rest in His children as they sojourn with a boundless optimism—an optimism that is buttressed by God’s sovereignty good. MOST HIGH GOD, Your ways know no change. Your goodness knows no limit. Your love knows no end. You delight in lavishing Your people with good gifts. These gifts aren’t merely the fulfillment of our shallow materialistic cravings, but these gifts are the true and sure fulfillment of our soul’s deepest longings. To know You is our greatest joy, but our hearts are hard to change, our minds are slow to learn, and our flesh is weak to follow. Lord, according to Your vast mercy and steadfast love, give us a greater insight into this heavenly reality. Let us be overwhelmed with optimism as we rest in the promises You have given to us. Let us not be discouraged by doubt, but strengthen by the knowledge of Your goodness. Let us not be ravaged by unbelief, but empowered by confident hope that You sovereignly operate all things for Your maximum glory and our maximum good. To You be all glory among all people through all generations.</summary></entry></feed>